<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anti-covenant, or a sad complaint concerning the new Oath or Covenant: presented in a letter to a dear and intimate friend, with earnest request for his advice and prayers. By a true loyall subject, and lover of the Parliament.</title>
            <author>True loyall subject and lover of the Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E60_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E60[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anti-covenant, or a sad complaint concerning the new Oath or Covenant: presented in a letter to a dear and intimate friend, with earnest request for his advice and prayers. By a true loyall subject, and lover of the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>True loyall subject and lover of the Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lychfield, printer to the University,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false; actually printed in London (Madan).</note>
                  <note>A reply to "A sacred vow and covenant taken by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament" promulgated by Parliament on 6 June 1643.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 14th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124454:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANTI-COVENANT, Or a ſad COMPLAINT Concerning The new <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Covenant:</hi> Preſented in a Letter to a dear and intimate Friend, with earneſt requeſt for his advice and Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a true loyall Subject, and lover of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Lychfield,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:124454:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124454:2"/>
            <head>The Anti-Covenant, <hi>Or,</hi> A ſad complaint concerning the new Oath, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare Friend and Brother, it is not unknowne to the world, as well as to thoſe ſober and pious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that are of our ſociety and acquaintance, what an honourable and reverend eſteem the very name of Parliament hath alwayes carried with us two, and how obſervant wee have beene of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, without diſputing their power or integrity. When the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation was enjoyned, we willingly and cheerfully tooke it, hoping therby to give ſufficient teſtimony both to the King and Parliament, and to all others that ſhould otherwiſe ſcruple it, of our love and zeale to the true eſtabliſhed Proteſtant Religion, of our loyalty and obedience to our gracious Sovereigne, of our honour and eſteeme of both Houſes of Parliament, and their juſt power and priviledges, and of our ſenſe and care of the rights and liberties of the ſubject: and this ſolemne Oath we have endeavoured to obſerve and keepe. When the Poll-money and great Subſidy were granted, both by King and Parliament, we moſt readily paid both. When the diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Ireland was recommended to us, we cheerefully contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Nay, when the Propoſitions were made to us, for plate, money and horſe, to fetch our good King from his evill Counſellours, (it being declared to us by ſome of the Members of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and others of their Commiſſioners, that his Majeſty was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to come from them, and that thoſe about him would flie from him upon the appearance of the Parliaments forces, without ſtriking one ſtroke) wee were perſwaded to lend liberally upon the Publike Faith towards that ſervice. And ſince that, upon ſeverall new ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, we have given ſuch credit to ſome Members of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpeeches, and to ſome Preachers, (whom they have countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, if not ſent amongſt us) that we have not with-holden from the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124454:3"/> Parliament what we have beene able to ſpare. Neither did we ſtop heere (though our ſpeed was by this time well taken off) but often and often ſince, partly out of feare, and partly out of hope, feare of being (after all this) reputed Malignants (a name more odious then Turke, Pagan, or Papiſt) and hope at laſt of an Accommodation, (a mercy too great for this ſinfull Nation as yet to pertake of) we have by our wives, kindred, or friends, more then once ſubminiſtred to the preſſing neceſſities of the Parliaments forces. But now (deare Brother) what ſhall we doe? When all that we have done hitherto, will keepe neither our houſes from plundering, nor our perſons from impriſonment, nor our names from being Malignant, nor our wives and children from beggery and miſery, unleſſe wee will wound our conſciences, and hazard our ſoules by horrid and palpable perjury. Oh, that we had but foreſeen this impoſing upon our ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, when firſt the opening of our purſes was called for; but it was Gods juſt judgement upon us for our ſinnes: firſt, to blinde us ſo long, till we had made a rod for our ſelves, and then to awe us with that rod, till our ſevere maſters have brought u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to that undou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bted triall, whether we feare God or them, whether wee love our ſoules, or our eſtates and liberties moſt. But what is the matter? Why read, and the Lord give you underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament have declared, That there hath beene, and now is, a Popiſh and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous plot, &amp;c. as it followeth in the Introduction and Covenant to be taken by the Armies and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>(With one clauſe more added in the Lords and Commons Oath, for their not laying downe Armes.) This is the new vow and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant taken by the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and voted by them to be taken by the Armies and Kingdome, together with the Introduction, declaring the grounds and reaſons inducing them thereunto.</p>
            <p>I know it is not fit for private men to be too inquiſitive into, much leſſe cenſorious of the decrees and ordinances of publike States, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be where ſuch decrees and ordinances concerne the ſoules and conſciences of men, and there every man is bound both diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to examine, and diſcreetly to judge whatſoever is injoyned him, before he ſubmit himſelfe thereunto; as alſo to counſell and adviſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124454:3"/> his brethren. Be pleaſed then, deare Brother (for ſo I have ever called and eſteemed you) to give me leave to acquaint you with my thoughts, both of this Oath and its Introduction: and wherein I erre (as who is infallible? not the Compoſers themſelves, much leſſe any private man, and leaſt of all my ſelfe, the weakeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand) I beſeech you be my gentle corrector, and friendly inſtructor. And firſt I begin with the Introduction.</p>
            <p>The reaſons and grounds of impoſing and taking this new Oath, heere alleadged, are principally theſe three:</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that the Lords and Commons have declared, that there hath beene, and now is, a Popiſh and traiterous plot for the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion; and the liberty of the Subject, and that in purſuance thereof, a Popiſh army hath been rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and is now on foot in divers parts of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Lords and Commons have further in a ſolemne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner declared, vowed, and covenanted, That in order to the ſecurity and preſervation of the true Proteſtant Religion, and liberty of the Subject, they will not conſent to the laying downe of Arms, ſo long as the Papiſts, now in open warre againſt the Parliament, ſhall by force of armes be protected againſt the juſtice thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For that the Lords and Commons have declared that there hath been a traiterous and horrid deſigne lately diſcovered by the great bleſſing and eſpeciall providence of God, of divers perſons to joyne themſelves with the Armies raiſed by the King, and to deſtroy the Forces raiſed by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, to ſurpriſe the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with the Suburbs, and by Armes to force the Parliament; all which reaſons are amplified with an aſſertion. That the ſaid Lords and Commons doe finde by conſtant experience, That many wayes of force and treachery are continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempted to bring to utter ruine and deſtruction the Parliament and Kingdome, and that which is deareſt, the true Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And then followes the inference or concluſion, that for the preventing and withſtanding the ſame, they have thought fit, that all &amp;c. ſhould binde themſelves each to other in a ſacred Vow and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in manner and forme as followeth, I A.B. <hi>In humility and reverence, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:124454:4"/>
            <p>The grounds and reaſons in their order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we are told, That the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament have declared, that there hath been, and now is a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and traiterous plot for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Liberty of the Subject. And that in purſuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp;c. This is the firſt <hi>Credendum,</hi> ſet foorth to uſher in our <hi>Juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> this we muſt believe, therefore thus and thus we muſt ſweare. But why muſt we believe this? becauſe the Lords and Common have Declared it. I ow the Lords and Commons my obedience in a ſubordinate way, next and immediatly under my King: but I do not yet know that I owe them my Faith, in that ſupreme way as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatſoever they declare. Nay, I know the contrary; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will be bold to examine the truth of this <hi>credendum,</hi> ſo far as I am able, before I give up my faith unto it.</p>
            <p>That there hath been in this Kingdome a Popiſh and trayterous plot, for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion, is recorded to us, and to our poſterities, with an Act of Parliament for an Anniverſary commemoration of our deliverance from the ſame. And I doubt not but there have beene many other plots ſince, to the ſame purpoſe, by the ſame faction, though God of his mercy hath diſappointed them ere they came to any viſible maturity: Neither will I altogether free the late potent Faction from intending ſome ſuch miſchiefe. Nay further, I am not very ſlow of heart to beleeve, that there is now at this preſent in this Kingdome a traiterous plot for the ſame purpoſe, which may as well be called a Popiſh, as an Anabaptiſticall, Browniſticall, or Separatiſticall plot, the Papiſts as well as the Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and other Separatiſts, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and contributing what they can thereunto, and all meeting and conſenting in the ſame poſitions and doctrines for the effecting thereof. For what <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of the Anabaptiſts and Papiſts, we find by wofull experience true of them all, <hi>Fratres ſunt, &amp; caudis conjuncta ſunt, vulpes, ſed capitibus diverſa: ſingunt ſeſe foris magnos hoſtes eſſe, cum tamen intus vere idem ſentiant, deceant, ac defendant,</hi> they are all bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and they are crafty foxes linked together by the tales, though their heads looke divers waies, they outwardly feigne themſelves to be great enemies each to other, but inwardly they doe verily think,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124454:4"/> teach, and maintaine one and the ſame thing. And all theſe though they pretend too much the liberty of the Subject, yet the truth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they intend only to inlarge their owne liberty and licentiouſneſſe, and to deſtroy the juſt liberty and property as well as the duty and loyalty of all Subjects whatſoever. Thus farre it is no difficult matter to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that there hath been and now is a plot for the ſubverſion of the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, and the liberty of the Subject, and to the lawfull defence of the ſame thus plotted againſt, I conceive my ſelfe already ſufficiently bound, not only by my duty, as I am a Proteſtant and a Subject, but alſo by my late Oath or Proteſtation, as I am thereby a new ſworne Proteſtant and Subject. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if that be the true cauſe why I ſhould take an oath, I have very lately for the ſame cauſe already taken one; and I humbly conceive that having made the former oath ſo lately, for their ſatisfaction who require this, they ought to reſt ſatisfied with the former, without ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any other; it being a ruled caſe in Law, <hi>Date jurejarund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non aliud quaritur quam, an juratum ſit, remiſſa quaſtiom an debentur, quaſt fatis probatum ſit jurejurand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> when once an oath is given, no further queſtion is to be made then whether the oath be taken or not, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtions of the proofe of what is controverted, are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as being proved ſufficiently by the very making oath thereof; and you well know what the Apoſtles rule in that caſe is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. an oath for confirmation is (at leaſt ought to be) to them (to thoſe who require the oath) an end of all ſtrife. And the multiplying of oaths is perillous as well to the impoſers, as to the takers.</p>
            <p>But to goe on with the firſt reaſon, That in purſuance of ſuch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a Popiſh plot, &amp;c. a Popiſh army hath been raiſed, and is now on foot in divers parts of this Kingdome; here my faith ſo ſtaggers that I cannot poſſibly keep it up to this aſſertion, and that for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe that an Army cannot truly be called a Popiſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, wherein not five of an hundred are Papiſts, unleſſe we take Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in that latitude as to involve all thoſe that imbrace, adhere to, and maintain the eſtabliſhed Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of England. And if five of an hundred in an Army being Papiſts may give the name of Popiſh to that Army, what name can we thinke of for that Army, wherein there are (beſides Papiſts) Anabaptiſts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124454:5"/> Browniſts, Familiſts, and other Sectaries an hundred for five true Reformed Proteſtants? Tis not denied but that there are now in the Kings Army too many that are Papiſts, and yet there are no more Papiſts in that army, then ought to be there; for being Subjects as well as Papiſts, they are bound both by the Lawes of God and of this Nation, to aſſiſt their King in his warres, both againſt forreign ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and againſt native rebels and uſurpers: and the King is bound to protect them againſt ſpoile, rapine, and other oppreſſion, aſwell as his other Subjects. It is, (I ſolemnly profeſſe) a ſore greefee to my ſoul (and ſo I am confident tis to all really religious Proteſtant ſouls beſides) that ever our King, who hath beene ſo long, and ſtill is, ſo eminent a Defender of the true Proteſtant Religion, ſhould neede the aſſiſtance of Papiſts, to defend his Royall perſon, honour, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; as tis a ſhame to our Religion it ſelf, that Papiſts ſhould ſhew their Loyalty and Allegiance to their King in ſuch a defence, when ſo many, that would be reputed the onely true Proteſtants, either take up or maintaine the taking up armes againſt him. This ſcandall to the Proteſtant Religion would ſcarce ever bee wiped of, were there not (bleſſed bee God for it) forty Proteſtants to one Papiſt, that cheerefully and valiantly aſſiſt the King in theſe preſent warres, with their lives and eſtates. Secondly, if the army raiſed by his Majeſty, and now on foot in divers parts of this Kingdome, bee a popiſh army, it were worth the knowing, when it became ſo, or when at leaſt it became to be ſo reputed, For that magnanimous and royall army which hath ever attended his ſacred perſon, I find ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Declarations of both Houſes of Parliament, wherein they who levied thoſe forces, and they that were levied, have beene called ill affected perſons; Cavaleers, Delinquents, Malignants, and the like; but ſcarce the name of Papiſts was for a long time mentioned in any of them. Since that, I finde Papiſts, a Jeſuiticall faction, prelaticall Clergy, and diſcontented perſons added to the former; and all called Aſſiſtants in and to the Forces prepared; but as yet they were not called a Popiſh Army; and it ſeemes there was not the leaſt cauſe why they ſhould be ſo ſtiled; for that no ſooner was the Name of Papiſts or Jeſuiticall faction, mentioned by them, as having ought to doe in that ſervice for the King, but preſently his Sacred. Majeſty cauſed a Proclamation to iſſue forth, given at his Court at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124454:5"/> Yorke Auguſt 10. 1642. expreſly commanding, that no perſon or perſons whatſoever, being Popiſh Recuſants, ſhould come to His Court, contrary to the Law in that caſe provided, or take any office or place, or liſt himſelfe as a ſouldier in His Service. And though the King at the time of that terrible bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell at Edgehill had admitted ſome few Papiſts of eminent abilities in command and conduct into His Service; yet He is graciouſly pleaſed to yeeld ſuch a faire and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable account thereof in His Declaration to all His loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects after His late victory againſt the Rebells on Sunday 23 of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1642. as muſt needs be to all that will credit the word of a King, moſt abundantly ſatisfactory. And ſince that battell, (that maske of fighting for the King being then blowne off with their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming powder) tis not to be endured in point of Honour by any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant that regards the honour of his Religion, that any ſhould ſay, the Papiſts have ſo outſtript the Proteſtants in loyalty, as to win the denomination of the Kings Army to be Popiſh from their ſuper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing therein: And (bleſſed be the Lord for it) they have not the leaſt cauſe ſo to brag, for what cauſe ſoever others have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo to declare. Then for the Kings Army in the Weſt ſo long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of that valiant and ſucceſſefull, religious and pious Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> I doe not remember that amongſt all the lyes and ſlanders, all the calumnies and reproaches, that have been preached or printed, any have yet been ſo wickedly impudent as to call that Popiſh, or to affirme that any knowne Papiſts are liſted in it. I am ſure both Houſes of Parliament in their Ordinances made againſt Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> and his Forces (<hi>viz.</hi> that in June 27. 1642. for the prevention of a moſt horrid, wicked and unnaturall deſigne purſued by Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and his adherents &amp;c. and that made the ſame day for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing of Malignants in the Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of Sommerſet, &amp;c.) never call any of thoſe that have aſſiſted him or joyned with him Papiſts, but only Rebells and Traitors. So that we are forced to looke into the Northerne parts to finde out this Popiſh Army: and for the Army in thoſe parts, though I finde ſome Diurnals, and other ſuch like lying and ſlanderous pamphlets, wherein that Army was called Popiſh, even at its firſt advancing into Yorkeſhire; yet I obſerved that the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament did not themſelves ſtile it ſo, no not in their Declaration for the ſuppreſſing of divers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124454:6"/> and other malignant perſons in the Counties of Yorke, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland, Weſtmerland, Cumberland, Lancaſhire, Cheſhire, &amp;c. Novemb. 23. 1642. They therein declare that the Papiſts, and other malignants, and ill affected perſons in thoſe Counties had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into an aſſociation, and cauſed great Forces both of horſe and foot to be raiſed to aid and aſſiſt the Popiſh and malignant party in thoſe parts; but for all this they doe not yet brand them with the name of a popiſh Army, afterwards indeed when they had found that the name of popiſh army ſpread abroad (as I but now ſaid) by Diurnalls and other lying and ſcandalous pamphlets (the conſtant preſſures to prepare the way for more au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hentick Declarations) had ſomewhat ſtartled and amazed the poore Country people: then we heare the ſtile of an Army of Papiſts under the command of the Earle of <hi>New-caſtle,</hi> made uſe of, as in that Declaration of the Houſe of Commons Decemb. 15. 1642. the Declaration of the Lords and Commons ſtill retaining their former ſtile. But paſſe by the originall of that army: Did that army as yet ever merit the name of Popiſh? That there were, and are more Papiſts in that army, then in all the Kings armies throughout the Kingdome I do verily beleeve; thoſe Counties out of which it was raiſed abounding with Papiſts more then other counties by far. And yet we have been aſſured from ſuch as deſerve our credit, that all the Papiſts in that army are not a handfull in compariſon of the whole body, not above one of fifty, and in all not ſo many as to make up two Regiments. But why five times ſo many Papiſts? (if there were ſo many in this Kingdome) ſhould not be admitted to take up armes for the defence of their Sovereigne, and rights and libertie of the Subject, I never yet heard any argument worth anſwering; nay how the papiſts, or any for them, could an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their not taking up armes in ſuch a caſe without incurring the guilt of high Treaſon, is paſt my reſolving. And for the Proteſtant Religion, which they ſo much hate, and the power and priviledge of Parliament, which they ſo much maligne; whereas it is objected that it cannot be thought, that they ſhould fight for the defence of either of them: I doe conceive that if they might be let alone quiet, and ſecure without intermedling, their love to either is not ſo great as to inflame their ſpirits to ſuch a hazard of their lives for their ſakes; but the preſſing neceſſities of the preſent times ingaging them in a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124454:6"/> War, and they finding the quarrell to be betwixt the ſafety of the Kings perſon, honour and eſtate, and the ambitious, ſeditious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious deſignes and attempts of ſome of His Subjects, betwixt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and ſome Anabaptiſts, Browniſts and other Sectaries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the enjoying the juſt power and priviledges of Parliament, together with their owne lives, goods and eſtates, and the being ſpoyled, robbed and deprived of all, or the moſt of theſe by the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power and priviledges of a few Lords and Commons; tis no wonder to ſee them to offer themſelves willingly to defend and maintain the former, rather then to endure &amp; ſuffer the latter. Beſides when the Proteſtants in a Kingdome are imbroyled in a civill war amongſt themſelves, or with any factious and ſchiſmaticall perſons, it would not be wiſdome in them to ſuffer the papiſts to ſit quiet and ſtill if they ſhould deſire it, leſt when they have weakned each other the papiſts prove too ſtrong for both. But for further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this point, I refer you to the Earle of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> his excellent Declaration to that purpoſe, and to that witty and ſolid lettter of a Worthy (whoſoever it was) to his friend in Leceiſterſhire.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things premiſed, thus cleared, I cannot but wonder what is meant by the popiſh army which hath been raiſed, and is now on foot in divers parts of this Kingdome: had we been told that there is ſuch an army flying in divers parts of this Kingdome, if we could not have ſeen it, it might happily have been imputed to the dulneſſe and weakneſſe of our ey-ſight, or to our want of that light, whereby ſome are able to diſcover things that never were, but to ſay there is ſuch an army on foot, and yet no more footſteps of it to be found, is to tell us little leſſe then a miracle, and but of little more credit then thoſe late miracles which ſome of our new apoſtles have boaſted of. Well but let us indulge them that name, ſeeing they who can call any things or perſons what they pleaſe, are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo to phraſe it. The army in the North whereof not above foure or five of an hundred are papiſts, is a popiſh army. But why then muſt it be beleeved that there is a popiſh army raiſed and on foot in divers parts of this Kingdome? Is it becauſe there are divers parts of the North wherein that army is, as <hi>York, Taacaſter, Pomfret, Wakefield,</hi> &amp;c. and all theſe are parts of this Kingdome; an excellent topicall argument to puzle a Freſh-man with; or is it becauſe they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124454:7"/> would have the poore long deceived people to beleeve, that foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the one part of the Kings army in the North is ſomewhat Popiſh, therefore all the Kings army that is now in ſeverall parts of this Kingdome, as Oxfordſhire, Dorſetſhire, Sommerſetſhire, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire, Cornwell, Staffordſhire and Worceſterſhire, &amp;c. conſiſts moſt of Papiſts? certainly it is in this latter ſenſe that they deſire the phraſe Popiſh army may be underſtood, or elſe it would prove but of very litle force to perſwade the common people (who bleſſed be God do generally abominate Popery) either to conceive ſo much evil of the Kings army, as they would poſſeſſe them withall, or elſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that there is from them any cauſe of fearing the ſubverſion of the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, and ſo of entring into an oath or covenant to doe ſuch and ſuch things as the new Oath requires. And by this time I hope you will excuſe me if I doe not beleeve that there is a popiſh army raiſed, and on foot in divers parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Thirdly, I abhor to let it enter into my thoughts, that any army is raiſed by the King (as is affirmed) for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Religion. The Preacher commands me in Gods name (whatſoever ſome preachers teach their people in their owne and their Maſters) not to curſe the King, no not in my thoughts, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 10.20. but ſhould I thinke that the King intends by His Army now on foot, or by any other way or meanes, to ſubvert the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion; though I ſhould not for all that curſe Him no not in my thoughts, yet I muſt needs think Him the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed King that ever breathed, He having made ſo many ſolemne oaths, vows and proteſtations, with moſt deep imprecations annexed both to live and dye in the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to maintaine and defend it in His Subjects. I will minde you only of that one in the head of His Army, Septem. 19. 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I promiſe in the preſence of Almighty God, and as I hope for his bleſſing and protection, that I will to the utmoſt of my power defend and maintaine the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, and by the Grace of God in the ſame will live and dye, &amp;c.</hi> And for the liberty of the Subject, together with the juſt priviledges and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of parliament, He did both at that time, and ſundry other with the like ſolemnly vow and ſweare their defence and maintainance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Now can it bee thought by any (but ſuch whoſe thoughts are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124454:7"/> thoughts of iniquity, <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.7.) that ſuch a conſtant and faithfull Defender of the true Proteſtant Religion for ſo many yeares againſt ſo many plots and attempts, intimated by this very Declaration, and after ſo many and ſo ſolemne oaths, vows and proteſtations, ſhould now raiſe an Army to ſubvert that Religion, and when it was raiſed to promiſe againe in the very head of that Army His beſt and utmoſt defence of the ſame, calling God to witneſſe with Him, and deſiring neither bleſſing nor protection from Him, but according as He reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make good that promiſe and proteſtation; doubtleſſe there is very nigh as much faith in Infidels, and as much charity in the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits as there is in theſe men that can beleeve ſuch a ſlander, or entertain ſuch a ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>In the Declaration of the Lords and Commons to the Kingdome, and to the World, Octob. 22. 1642. they account the profeſſing of any thing in the ſight of God, the ſtrongeſt obligation that any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and the moſt ſolemne publike faith that any ſuch ſtate as a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament can give. They then that will not credit the like profeſſion made by a King, muſt neither thinke him a Chriſtian, nor eſteem him a King. Beſides, were there any ſo wickedly uncharitable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall, as to imagine that the King had an intention to ſubvert the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion. Yet how can they think both him, and his evill counſellors, together with the Popiſh party about him (as every pamphlet takes the liberty, moſt traiterouſly, to pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him and his royall attendants) to be all ſo weak and ſimple, as to rayſe an army for the purſuance of that intent, juſt at that time, when greater forces of Proteſtants (as they would be thought) were either actually rayſed, or ready to riſe, then he or they could by the eye of fleſh ſee any poſſibility of levying; and when he wanted both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and armes for thoſe few, that he might hope to levie: without doubt, if there had beene any ſuch purpoſe, that time of all other would not have been choſen for the opportunity. Theſe reaſons are of ſuch force with me, that the firſt reaſon alleadged for the taking this Oath ſeemes to mee, (to ſay the leaſt of it) altogther unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            <p>Proceed wee on to the ſecond, it may be that is more ingaging. The Lords and Commons have further in a ſolemne manner, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vowed, and covenanted, that in order to the ſecurity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124454:8"/> of the true Proteſtant Religion, and liberty of the Subject, they will not conſent to the laying downe armes, ſo long as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts now in open warre againſt the Parliament, ſhall by force of armes be protected from the juſtice thereof.</p>
            <p>Before this reaſon will downe with me for a perſwading reaſon to the taking this Oath, I muſt bee ſatisfied, if poſſible, in theſe <hi>Quaeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quaer.</hi> What doe the Lords and Commons meane by that clauſe. In order to the ſecurity and preſervation of the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, &amp;c. Doe they meane that they will never conſent to the laying downe armes, &amp;c. No, not for the ſecurity and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the true Proteſtant Religion: or that becauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the true Proteſtant Religion cannot bee ſecured and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſo long as the Papiſts now in open warre ſhall, &amp;c. That therefore they will not conſent to the laying downe armes, ſo long &amp;c. Or is this, In order to, &amp;c. uſed heere for ſome evading reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Ieſuits have conſtantly uſed their, <hi>In ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> (they being the only men, that I can recall to mind for the preſent, that ever uſed this kind of reſtriction, or, rather indeed, this faſt and looſe knot of an oath) that ſo they may evade ſome oathes formerly taken, or the power of this, in caſe they can get a faire gloſſe to bee made upon theſe termes: charity and reverence command mee to take the beſt interpretation: but an oath ſhould bee framed in ſuch plaine cleare tearmes, as might be underſtood by all the takers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without much difficulty of expoſition: but to leave that to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quar.</hi> Whom doe the Lords and Commons underſtand by Papiſts now in open warre againſt the Parliament? whether legally convicted Papiſts only, or all Papiſts at large? If all Papiſts at large, (as I conceive they meane no leſſe,) my</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quaere</hi> is: Whether only knowne profeſſed Papiſts, properly ſo called? or alſo all ſuppoſed, ſuſpected Papiſts, commonly, ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? If the former</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether they have proceeded againſt all ſuch that are now in the Kings army, according to the eſtabliſhed Law of this Kingdome, and requiring juſtice to be done upon them, they have beene by force of armes protected from the execution thereof?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:124454:8"/>5. <hi>Quar.</hi> How or where doth it appeare that there have been or are, any ſuch ſo protected, eſpecially to ſuch a number, as that the protecting of them ought to move the great Actors and Contrivers for the Kingdomes peace, for that cauſe to vowe and covenant to continue this unchriſtian, unnaturall warre, till they be delivered up to their juſtice.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether the Queenes Majeſty her ſelfe, bee not one of thoſe protected Papiſts chiefly aymed at?</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Quar.</hi> If by Papiſts they meane all that are ſuppoſed, ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and by divers termed Papiſts: whether all thoſe that are called Malignants, or Delinquents, or diſaffected perſons, and ſo all that are eyther of the Kings army, or have beene ayding and aſſiſting to them, are not by them reckoned in that number? So that if the King would deliver up to their juſtice, all that are Papiſts indeed, (even to his deare Queene) within all his armies, yet if hee will not with them deliver up alſo all his whole armies themſelves, or at leaſt as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them as they ſhall require, they will not ſtill thinke themſelves bound by this vow and covenant, not to lay downe their armes, or to give their conſent thereto?</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Quar.</hi> Whether the King be not bound in conſcience, by the Lawes of God, and of this Kingdome, by his owne ſolemn vows and proteſtations, and by the common law of Nature (too much pleaded by ſome in theſe dayes, even againſt the law of Grace it ſelfe) to defend and protect, and that by force of armes, need ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, not only his owne deare Queene, but all his faithfull and loyall Subjects, both Papiſts and others, ſuch eſpecially as repaire to him for his ſacred perſons defence and ſafety, as well as for their owne protection, and the preſervation of their rights and liberties?</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether the King on the one part being ſo bound to defend and protect both his Queene and the reſt now named; and the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament, having on the other part, taken up Armes, to force all thoſe perſons from the Kings defence and protection, and bound themſelves by a ſolemne new oath, never to lay down their armes againe, ſo long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny ſuch perſons are ſo protected, whether, I ſay, can there bee poſſibly, any hope conceived of peace and accommodation, either by way of Treaty, or any other way whatſoever, without the effuſion of infinite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124454:9"/> ſtreams of blood, ſo much as will make any Chriſtians heart to bleed, but to think on it, and his very joints to looſe, and his knees to knock one againſt another, to have any hand in it, knowing what the hand of God hath written againſt bloodſhed?</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Quaer.</hi> This being the true caſe of this Kingdome at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whether is not this ſecond reaſon of the Lords and Commons making ſuch a new covenant, as will, (if ſeconded by ours) coſt the expence of ſo much of our owne, and fellow-brethrens blood, rather a ſtrong reaſon, why we ſhould abhorre this new oath, by whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is taken, then any the leaſt inducement to perſwade us to take it.</p>
            <p>Before I part from this reaſon, ſuffer me, I beſeech you, to be ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle a few teares on it, and to pant forth a few broken ejaculations concerning thoſe that alleadge it: Mourne on my ſoule. Oh, that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountayne of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9 1. How are thy mighty men, O England, fallen in the midſt of the battell? 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.25. Yea, how are they ſlaine from one end of the Land to the other? How have the carkaſes of thy people beene made as dung upon the open field? Oh thou ſword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou be quiet? put up thy ſelfe into thy ſcabbard, reſt, and be ſtill. But how canſt thou be quiet, ſeeing the Lord hath given thee a charge againſt this Land? O God of mercies, as well as Lord of Hoſts, we acknowledge that we have deſerved it, and we ſee to our terrour, that they, whom we too much relied on for the ſetling our peace, have ſworne themſelves, and would ſwear us into a perpetuall warre; but we hope thou haſt not yet paſſed ſuch a decree againſt us. Spare us therefore, we humbly beſeech thee, oh ſpare thy people, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy pretious blood, and let not the ſword be made drunke with blood any longer, nor let drunkenneſſe of ſpirit, we intreat thee, ſeaſe upon our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and our wiſe men, our Captaines and our Rulers, and our mighty men, to cauſe them to ſleepe a perpetuall ſleep; but Lord doe thou awaken both them and us, that we may yet at laſt in this our day of viſitation, ſee and ſeeke thoſe things that concerne our peace.</p>
            <p>And now I goe on to the third reaſon or ground. The Lords and Commons have declared, that there hath beene a treacherous and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124454:9"/> horrid deſigne lately diſcovered, by the great bleſſing and eſpeciall providence of God, of divers perſons to joine themſelves with the armies rayſed by the King, and to deſtroy the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, to ſurpriſe the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with the Suburbes, and by armes to force the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>If there hath beene a treacherous and horrid deſigne lately diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the great bleſſing and eſpeciall providence of God, we are all bound upon the knowledge thereof, to magnifie Gods mercy and goodneſſe, and to extoll his power and providence for it, and that man ſhall not want for a curſe that ſhall ſlight or undervalue ſo great a bleſſing: but I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould therupon, or for that cauſe, ruſh preſently into a vow or covenant, and run our Soules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a farre greater hazard then our Bodies were delivered from. But, it may be, it was ſuch a treacherous and horrid deſigne, as may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a vow and covenant forthwith to bee made by us: Tis fit wee ſhould throughly examine whether it be or not, leſt otherwiſe we be guilty of taking Gods name in vaine in the higheſt degree. All that is made knowne to us concerning this treacherous and horrid deſign by the Introduction to this oath (from which the takers thereof are to receive their ſureſt information, and by which principally they are to be induced to take it) is only this. There was a deſigne of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons for theſe fowre ends: 1. To joyn themſelves with the armies rayſed by the King. 2. To deſtroy the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons in Parliament. 3. To ſurpriſe the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with the Suburbes. 4. To force the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by armes. Now let us looke upon this deſigne a while, with a ſingle, cleare, open eie, neither ſquint nor blood-ſhot, neither with a magnifying, nor with a formidable-falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-rendring glaſſe, and diſcover if we can, wherein the treacherouſneſſe and horridneſſe of it lies. For the firſt intent of the deſigne. The joyning of divers perſons with the armies rayſed by the King, tis ſo far from treachery and horridneſſe, that he that is an Engliſh man, can ſcarce avoyd the being a Traytor, and ſo moſt horrid, that doth not ſo joine himſelfe with thoſe Armies in ſome way or other, wherein he is beſt able to doe his Sovereigne ſervice; and for the diſcovery thereof tis well knowne not to be ſo lately as is pretended, the Lords and Commons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124454:10"/> themſelves having declared it often and often, and that long ſince in ſundry Declarations. But that either thoſe perſons, or thoſe armies with whom they joine, doe aime at, or intend the deſtroying the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, or the ſurpriſing the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes, or the forcing the Parliament by armes (though they have all three beene a long time ſpoken of, and two of them again and again inſiſted upon by the Lords and Commons in their Orders and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances) hath never to this day been prooved, but on the contrary, ſo deeply and ſolemnly have all theſe aimes beene proteſted and ſworn againſt by the King himſelfe, and are ready (if that would give any ſatisfaction) to be diſclaimed and renounced upon the oaths of thoſe armies, and the perſons joyning with them; that were all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but concealed, jealouſies and feares as eaſie to be removed, as thoſe three now pretended, all ſuch forces on both ſides would bee ſoone disbanded, and theſe unnaturall and unchriſtian warres ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended. This indeed is to be expected, and cannot well be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if after ſo many and ſo gratious overtures of peace, pardon, and all ſweet accommodation made by his Sacred Majeſty, the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons ſhall not only refuſe to lay down their armes, but uſe them (as hitherto they have) to the ſubverſion both of the Diſcipline and Order, as alſo of the Doctrine and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God eſtabliſhed in our Church, to indangering the Kings perſon, the conſumption of his treaſure and eſtate, and to the damage and ruine of his whole Kingdome: and if the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with the Suburbs thereof, ſhall, as formerly they have, joine with them, and ayd and aſſiſt them, both with men, mony, armes, and other warlike proviſion, and if ſome of the Members of either or both Houſes of Parliament, ſhall countenance, encourage, juſtifie and maintaine all theſe ungodly actions, againſt his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall Perſon, Crowne, and Dignity, Who can blame either thoſe armies rayſed by the King, or thoſe perſons that joyne with them, if they ſhall do their utmoſt, to ſubdue or deſtroy thoſe forces, to ſurpriſe or bring into ſubjection thoſe Cities, and to force or ſome other way to reduce thoſe Members to their duty and allegiance? Nay, what Chriſtian or Heathen Subjects would not in ſuch a caſe crie out againſt them now, and riſe up in judgement againſt them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124454:10"/> heereafter, if they ſhould doe otherwiſe? And therefore if this bee the Deſigne ſo much talked of, as for my part I believe it is, what loyall ſubject can ſay, he had no hand in it? and who but hee that hath had no hand in it, dare ſay, it was eyther treacherous or horrid? Oh, but Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> hath declared it ſo to be, in his ſpeech at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-hall in London, <hi>June</hi> 8. 1643. wherein hee ſhewes the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Deſigne to be no leſſe then theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To take into their cuſtody the Kings Children, that are in or about London.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To lay hold on all thoſe that they thought could ſtand in their way, as the Lord <hi>Say,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> of the Houſe of Lords; and of the Houſe of Commons, (beſides the Lord Major) Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hampden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> and (which he acknowledgeth to be an honour to him to be named) Mr. <hi>Pym.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To ſeiſe on the Committee of the Militia, and the Magazines within London and Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To releaſe all the priſoners committed by the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To make a Declaration to ſatisfie the people.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Lord for it, heer is no intention diſcovered of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering or butchering any of the Kings children, or of any of the Citizens, or of any of the Members of either Houſes of Parliament; no not of the perſons named; neither is there heere any reſolution intimated of blowing up any part of London or Weſtminſter, or of firing any houſe therein, but only of taking the Kings Children into their cuſtody, of laying hold on certaine Lords and Commons, and of ſeiſing the Militia, &amp;c. and this, it ſeemes, in the ſenſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of this Oath, is to deſtroy the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons, to ſurpriſe the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, and by armes to force the Parliament, and all this a treacherous and horrid Deſign. But how is that made good? Surely the taking of the Kings Children into their cuſtody, (if it were any part of the Deſigne) is not thought by the Lords and Commons themſelves, to have much treachery or horridnes in it, howſoever Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> (to ſhew his ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant care of thoſe hopefull branches, for their Royall Stemmes ſake) was pleaſed to make that the firſt branch of that treacherous and horrid Deſigne: neither can the releaſing of the priſoners com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Parliament, (if any ſuch juſtice were purpoſed) bee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124454:11"/> well judged to have much treachery or horridneſſe in it: for alas, poore unarmed men all, (men abhorring treachery and all horrid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes ſo much, that the greateſt cauſe of moſt of their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is their declaming againſt, and not contributing or conſenting unto that Deſigne, which they know to be both trayterous and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid) what could they have done, had they beene releaſed? It would be ſafeſt for them, if there ſhould be any combuſtion or mutiny in the City or Suburbs (which God forbid) not to come forth of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons though they were intreated. Perhaps indeed the making of a Declaration to ſatisfie the people, might have advanced the Deſigne not a little; for, it ſeemes by Mr. <hi>Pyms</hi> ſpeech, it was ſome notable, faire, well-compos'd peece, carrying a moſt ſpecious ſhew of much intended goodneſſe: <hi>viz.</hi> The preſervation of Religion, the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Kings Prerogative, and the preſervation of the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Subject, and the priviledges of Parliament; and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers thereof were very confident (as Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> intimates) of the peoples crediting and believing it: for that a thouſand of them were to be printed, and they to be ſet upon Poſts and Gates in the moſt conſiderable places of the City, and to be diſperſed, as much as they could, againſt the time that the Deſigne ſhould be put in execution, as if that would cleare all their intentions, and convince the people of their integrity in undertaking that buſineſſe. And to tell you my judgement of it, for ſo much as I can collect from Mr. <hi>Pym,</hi> it was ſuch a piece of a treacherous Deſigne, that Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> was afraid, that it would have gone neer to have betrayed the people into their wits againe; perhaps into their Religion and loyalty, if not into ſome of their Eſtates and Liberties: and therefore he lets it not paſſe without paſſing this moſt obſervable Sentence on it, ratified from his owne practiſe and experience. There be no deſignes bee they never ſo ill, but they doe put on a maske of ſome good; for that which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and apparantly evill, hath no congruity with the will of man, and therefore the worſt of evills are undertaken under a ſhew and ſhadow of goodneſſe: ſound doctrine, and an excellent caution, I confeſſe: would to God the people had beene better inſtructed in it, and more mindfull of it in theſe times: but yet with reverence to that great Speaker be it ſpoken, If that intended Declaration which he ſpeakes of, were worthy of no other blame, but its appearing ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124454:11"/> extraordinary faire and ſpecious (as were there any other reall exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption againſt it, doubtleſſe that quick-ſighted Gentleman would not have balked it) I ſee no reaſon, why becauſe by often and late expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it hath beene found, that ſome Declarations full of Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Miſchiefe, have appeared faire in ſhew, therefore this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration full of loyalty and goodneſſe, ſhould be thought treacherous and miſchievous, only becauſe it was faire in appearance. But then for the other two parts of the deſigne, <hi>viz.</hi> the laying hold on thoſe perſons named, and the ſeiſing upon the Militia and Magazines of London and Weſtminſter, together with thoſe that now are the prime managers and diſpoſers thereof; that theſe were the ready way to deſtroy the forces rayſed by the Parliament, to ſurpriſe thoſe Cities, and to force the Parliament, ſeemes clearly to be demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the forenamed City Orator. Take only the extract of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in the caſe. The ſeiſing upon the Militia of London and Weſtminſter, muſt needs be a ſurpriſing of thoſe Cities themſelves: the ſurpriſing of thoſe Cities, is a deſtroying of the forces rayſed by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, if not by force, yet by want of ſupply and maintenance, (obſerve by the way, what maner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction intended againſt the Parliaments forces, is heere acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged:) and if the forces rayſed by the Parliament, were once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, (that is, wanted ſupply and maintenance) and then (which is the moſt terrible) if thoſe named Members of both Houſes, and ſome few others of their temper and ſpirit, together with their faſt friends and ſworne ſlaves of the City, were once layd hold on, the reſt of both thoſe Honourable Houſes, being but the carkaſe and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Parliament, (as Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> in his Common-hall ſpeech, doth not only call, but labour to prove them) alas, what would they doe? certainly that carkaſe would move in no other motion; then accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the returning ſoule, (the known Lawes of the Land, and the juſt priviledges of Parliament) would ſteere it, and not according as every furious and factious ſpirit ſhould thinke to hurry it: and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe, that ſhadow would not follow any other, then its owne full, compleat, repreſentative Body; not a cloſe Committee, or a few ſeditious, rebellious Citizens. And then tis likely, there would be a ſweet correſpondence betwixt the King and them, the King yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them as much, as they would in due obſervance be willing to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124454:12"/> propound to him, and they granting to the King as much as he could with honour deſire of them. And heer truly would be ſuch a forcing of the Parliament, as this Kingdome hath not knowne theſe many yeeres: and yet all this is farre enough from a treacherous and horrid deſigne. Only thus much (we humbly thanke him for it) Mr. <hi>Pyms</hi> diſcovery renders viſible to every eye, that will not ſhut it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light. That were but the Militia of the Cities of London and Weſtminſter, with their Magazines in ſome mens hands, with whom, (as hath beene at large declared by able and ſound Lawyers) the King may of right intruſt it; and were but the maintenance and ſupply which thoſe two Cities ſubminiſter to the Parliaments army, withheld or ſtopt, and then (which would follow of it ſelfe, unleſſe they made the more haſte to flie from it) were but ſome few Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both Houſes, together with ſome buſie Citizens, laid hold on, and laid up in hold, (as there are priſons enough, and to ſpare, ready provided, in and about London) till they could be brought to a legall triall for that Treaſon, whereof by Proclamation they ſtand charged by the King, our Land would ſoone enjoy her glorious reſt and peace again: nay, happily if the laſt were but acted, we ſhould ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſee the laſt Act of this bloody Tragedy (wherein this miſerable Kingdome is ingaged) hiſt off, and beaten off the Stage, by its grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Applauders. And therefore were thoſe few perſons, at whom the late ſtrange, treacherous, horrid deſigne aymed, men of that pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards God, and of that tender compaſſion and bowels towards their bleeding and periſhing Country that they pretend to be, they would, <hi>Jonah</hi>-like, (now they ſee the Church and State, wherein they are imbarqued, ready to be overwhelmed or ſplit, by the boyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous waves and tempeſtuous windes of theſe raging times, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for their ſakes) deliver themſelves up to be caſt forth, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe expoſed, even to death it ſelfe, that there might be a calm: and likewiſe they that have hitherto rowed them, (now they have ſhewne their love and affection to them, in rowing ſo hard to ſet them ſafe on ſhore, and ſee that they cannot, the ſea working and growing more and more tempeſtuous againſt them, by the mighty coworking of him that commands both ſea and wind, and they obey him) me thinks they ſhould, (after prayers and cries to God, to keep t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m from the guilt of their blood) not take them up, and caſt them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124454:12"/> forth into the ſea, but ſhut them up, and keepe them ſafe, till they ſee whether a juſt and legall triall, (ſo often demanded) will judge them worthy to be caſt forth or not: and if it appear they ſo deſerve, I hope it is neither traiterous nor horrid to ſay, it were better that milſtones were hanged about their necks, and they caſt into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the ſea, then that the whole Kingdome for their ſakes ſhould be caſt away and periſh.</p>
            <p>And thus we have viewed the three maine pillars upon which the ſtructure of this new oath is built. Now fearing leſt all three might prove too weake to raiſe ſuch a weighty building upon, there is a buttreſſe or by-arch joyned to them all for their better underprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping plaiſtred over with theſe words. And the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons finding by conſtant experience, that many wayes of force and treachery are continually attempted to bring to utter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction the Parliament and Kingdom, and that which is deareſt the true Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>This Arch is made up of the ſame materialls with the three maine pillars, and ſo it is not materiall whether any other examination bee made of it or not, for they ſtand and fall together, only we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, if you pleaſe, that whereas we were told but of one Popiſh and traiterous plot that hath been and now is for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion, &amp;c. as alſo but of one treacherous and horrid deſigne, and that lately diſcovered to deſtroy &amp;c. here we are invited (if not commanded) to beleeve that many wayes of force and treachery are continually attempted for the ſame ends. It ſeems theſe many wayes of force and treachery that have been found by conſtant experience to be continually attempted to bring to utter ruine and deſtruction the Parliament and Kingdome, and the true Proteſtant Religion, were ſuch, as were not worthy of the name of plots or deſignes, at leaſt not Popiſh plots or horrid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes; or elſe they were very unworthy, who having found them out, would not to this day diſcover what they were; for beſides the bringing up of the Northerne Army, and the King going once more then ordinarily attended to ſurpriſe the five Members (which muſt needs be included in the Popiſh and traiterous plot firſt mentioned, and hath been againe and againe anſwered by His ſacred Majeſty) we never heard (till now this traiterous and horrid deſigne was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124454:13"/> of any one way of force or treachery, that ever was aſſayed to compaſſe any of the ends here declared: But ſomething muſt bee ſaid to ſcare the people (fit be poſſible) quite out of their wits, loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Religion and all, or elſe this grand plot of plots, and deſigne of deſignes, the taking of this new Oath will hardly take effect.</p>
            <p>Theſe premiſes being laid, this concluſion is inforced, That for the preventing and withſtanding the ſame, they have thought fit, that all, who are true hearted, and lovers of their Country ſhould binde themſelves each to other in a ſacred Vow and Covenant, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now although (as you know) the premiſes being falſe, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion alwayes falls of it ſelfe; yet becauſe there is more crowded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this concluſion, then can be inferred from the premiſes, and we are like to be forced to hold to the concluſion whatſoever the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are, it will not be amiſſe to ſpeake a word or two of that alſo.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is declared that for the preventing, &amp;c. The Lords and Commons have thought fit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here are very gentle termes, is though the Contrivers of this oath deſired only to intimate their opinion of the conveniency of taking it, &amp; would compell none to it, but leave it to the liberty of every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience whether they would take it or not; when as tis to be feared, a few dayes experience will aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded is the Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth of this Nation, and either take this oath, and be perjured, (if not worſe) or take it not, and be plundred, impriſoned, if not bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from houſe and County, will be all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e liberty our oppreſſed conſciences ſhall obtaine. But not to prejudge or propheſie. Take the expreſſion as it is, They have thought fit ſuch a Vow or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſhould be made by all that are, &amp;c. and tis not fit that any that are ſuch ſhould ſcruple it. Well, but if the taking this ſolemne oath, or making this ſacred Vow and Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nant, be but a thing fitting and convenient, and not of ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinary, much leſſe of extream neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: it hath ever been a ruled caſe in Divinity, that a ſolemne oath, ſacred vow or covenant ought not in ſuch a caſe to be required or made. Beſides, (which I muſt againe and againe put you in minde of) if all, that is declared in the introduction to this oath were true, &amp; knowne to us all ſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: We have lately ſo ſolemnly proteſted and ſworne in that proteſtation or oath recommended unto us from the Houſe of Commons, That to our power, and as far as lawfully we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124454:13"/> may, we will oppoſe, and by all good wayes and meanes endeavour to bring to condigne puniſhment all ſuch, as ſhall either by force, plots, conſpiracies or otherwiſe, doe any thing contrary to the true reformed Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed, (ſo far eſpecially as that is oppoſite to Popery, or Popiſh innovations) or againſt His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties royall Perſon, Honour, and Eſtate, or againſt the power and priviledges of Parliament, or againſt the lawfull rights and liberties of the Subject, or againſt any perſon that made that proteſtation in whatſoever he ſhould doe in the lawfull purſuance of the ſame; that if there be no more aimed at in the impoſing this oath, then what is lawfull, juſt, and faire, in any or all thoſe pretended grounds or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alledged in the introduction for that purpoſe, we have already as deeply and firmly ingaged and bound our ſelves thereunto as any Chriſtian can poſſibly require us. They have but little charity, who after an oath made of ſuch and ſuch things ſo lately, ſhall now againe require another oath to be taken for the confirmation of the ſame things. Furthermore, when the King in his going againſt the Scots, did at York cauſe an oath to be tendred to the Lords and others then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending His ſacred Perſon, it was anſwered by the Lords, and that anſwer accepted and reſted in by His Majeſty, that they humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that no oath ought to be tendred either to them, or to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther His Majeſties Subjects, but what Himſelfe and the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia. had firſt conſented unto. And (which cannot be ſo ſoone forgotten) at the beginning of this Parliament, that unhappy oath compoſed by that unfortunate Convocation, and aſſented unto by the King, was by the Houſe of Commons (and by the Houſe of Lords too, if I much miſtake not) utterly damned, (as the expreſſion then was) and the Members of the Convocation judged guilty of little leſſe then a premunire, for that it was by them decreed to be tendred to the Subject without any act paſſed in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the ſame. We beſeech them therefore, that that which was thought reaſon and Law then, may not be ſo ſoone not only thought none, but the flat contrary thought fit, and practiſed by the ſame perſons.</p>
            <p>It followes in the inference, That all that are true hearted and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their Country ſhould binde themſelves, &amp;c,</p>
            <p>Theſe are conjuring words to the Country people, and of very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124454:14"/> large compaſſe; had they declared, that all that are true hearted; and lovers of the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion, ſhould binde themſelves, &amp;c. it might have made Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and ſuch like to have ſtartled at it; whereas this calling upon all that are true hearted and lovers of their Country, may chance to fetch them and all in; and the truth is, let each part of this oath bee throughly ſcanned, there will be very little or nothing found in it, but what all Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, and Browniſts, that thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their owne ſenſe true hearted and lovers of their Country, and have not taken the oath of Allegiance, Supremancy, and the laſt Proteſtation, may more ſafely ſweare, vow, or covenant, then they that are true hearted Proteſtants, and reall lovers of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of England. All that I can ſee which may cauſe them to ſcruple it, is this: They muſt ſweare that they do in their conſciences beleeve, That the forces raiſed and continued by the two Houſes of Parliament, are raiſed and continued for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, &amp;c. and that they will aſſiſt thoſe forces againſt the forces raiſed by the King. And I beſeech you, why may not Papiſts, Anabaptiſts and Browniſts, both beleeve this in their conſciences, and yeeld this aſſiſtance, as well, or better then any true hearted Proteſtant, that loves the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed. And it muſt needs be thought very fit, that ſuch a ſacred vow and covenant be made and taken by us true hearted Subjects and lovers of the true Proteſtant Religion, for the defence of our Religion and Liberties, which ſuch profeſſed enemies to our Religion and Liberties, may with more ſafety of conſcience make or take then we.</p>
            <p>But not to dwell any longer upon the Introduction. In the laſt place, it will not be amiſſe to obſerve, under what Names this new Oath is recommended unto us: <hi>viz</hi> Under the names of a ſacred vow and covenant. I doe not uſe to boggle at Names; but theſe are the times of Jealouſies and Feares, and it cannot bee expected but ſome will be fearefull and jealous of the Declarations and Actions of the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament, as well as they have beene, and ſtill are of others; and therefore, I truſt, it is a pardonable ſinne, (if any) to ſay, I like this Oath ſomwhat the worſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124454:14"/> for its appearing to us, under that borrowed name of ſacred vow and covenant, and not under its owne proper name, An Oath. I ever ſuſpected the ſhifting of Names; and I would faine know ſome reaſon (if it might be imparted to ſuch a one as I am) why it ſhould not (being an atteſtation, or calling God to witnes for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what is aſſerted or promiſed, which is as full, compleate, and formall an Oath, as can be taken) be tendred unto us under the name of an oath, rather then under the name of a ſacred vow and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant? Is it to facilitate the taking of it? there being many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the ordinary ſort of people, that feare the taking of an oath, eſpecially a ſolemne, publike oath, having beene often taught the perill of it; who will never ſtartle at the making a vow or covenant, being leſſe inſtructed, if not altogether ignorant of the nature of it. Or are not theſe borrowed names uſed, to hold the people more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and firmly to this oath, when tis once taken? So that, if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after this oath taken, ſhould begin to doubt, whether it bee not flatly contrary to their oath of Allegiance, to their oath of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to their late Proteſtation, (as without doubt it is) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon either thinke this oath abſolutely void, or queſtion whether this or the former oathes were the more obliging, it would be an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which the Time-ſerving-Preachers would not let ſlip, to tell the people, That this their laſt oath is to be held to, before all their former: becauſe it is not only an oath, as they were, but alſo a ſacred vow and covenant, I am ſure leſſe advantages have beene made uſe of by thoſe new Teachers. But no more of the Name, wiſhing from my ſoule that it had never beene named amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Come we to the Oath it ſelfe. Concerning which, for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of my owne conſcience, and the conſciences of as many as you ſhall pleaſe to acquaint therewith, I deſire that one rule for the right taking of an oath may be throughly conſidered, and each part of this preſent Oath, examined according to that Rule. The Rule is that of Gods own preſcribing, by his Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> 4.2. Thou ſhalt ſweare, The Lord liveth, in Truth, in Iudgement, and in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: that is, in few words: Thou ſhalt ſweare to nothing, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God, who liveth for ever, as a witneſſe thereunto, but what is True, and what thou knoweſt and art ſure of, and what is juſt and righteous. Theſe three qualifications ought to bee the boundaries
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:124454:15"/> and limits of every oath; and hee ſinneth highly againſt the expreſſe Command of God, and ſo hazards his Soule in a moſt perillous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that fayleth in any one of theſe. According unto theſe then, let us in the Name of God examine the ſeverall parts of this new Oath.</p>
            <p>Firſt, every man that taketh this Oath is required to declare, and that in reverence and humility to the Divine Majeſty, and (as tis in the cloſe of the oath) in the preſence of Almighty God the ſearcher of all hearts, as he will anſwer at the great day when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed, his hearty ſorrow for his owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes of this Nation, &amp;c. and that his true intention is by Gods grace to endevour the amendment of his owne wayes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I propound theſe two <hi>Quaeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How thouſands and ten thouſands in this Nation can ſwear this in Truth, when as, poore ſouls, if all ſhould take this oath that are by this Ordinance required, tis to be feared there would be no fewer, whoſe very hearts would give their mouthes the lie, and whoſe very immediat actions would teſtifie againſt them to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: for, alas, how few are there who attaine to that height of grace and goodnes, as to be heartily ſorry either for their owne ſins, or the ſinnes of the Nation? Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them (ſayd God once of Iſrael, when they all promiſed that they would heare whatſoever God ſpake to Moſes and doe it) that they would feare me, and keepe all my commandements alwaies, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever: and, oh, that there were now ſuch an heart in us all of this Nation, will all good men wiſh, that we would all in earneſt be heartily ſorry for our owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes of this Nation; and that wee did really intend an amendment of our owne wayes: for then, to bee ſure, it would be well with us, and with our children after us. But for ſo many thouſands, nay the moſt of us, to declare, and ſweare this in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, when both God that ſearcheth our hearts, and our own hearts themſelves know, that it is not ſo: what will this doe, but infinitely adde to our ſinnes, and provoke God to adde to our calamities and judgements both perſonall and Nationall? How many fowle, abominable, crying ſinnes are there, whereof you and I know multitudes, (I would we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124454:15"/> could exempt the Impoſers of this new Oath) to bee deeply guilty, which the moſt of them will not acknowledge to be ſinnes, but juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie themſelves in them, ſo far as they are from being heartily ſorry for them, or intending any amendment of them. As for inſtance, uncharitablenes, lying, ſlandering, rapine, oppreſſion, diſobedience, blooſhed, and rebellion; and yet they that are moſt conſcious of ſuch crimes will, (tis likely) with the firſt declare or ſweare in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, and as they will anſwer it at the great day, &amp;c. that they are heartily ſorry for their owne ſinnes, &amp;c. and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend amendment. Thus whilſt we profeſſe to enter into a ſacred co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and by that to binde our ſelves to bewaile and forſake our ſinnes, (the acknowledged cauſes of our preſent calamities and judgements) we doe but mocke God, ſpeaking words and ſwearing falſly in making a covenant, which makes our judgements to grow the more, ſpringing up like hemlocke in furrowes of the field, <hi>Hoſen</hi> 10.4. Let us then pray, and that earneſtly, that God would bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, according to his promiſe <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31. to make a new covenant with us, and to put his law in our inward parts, and write it in our hearts, or (as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> expreſſeth that covenant <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11. 19.20.) that he would give us one heart, and put a new ſpirit within us, and take the ſtony heart out of our fleſh, and give us an heart of fleſh, that we may walke in his ſtatutes, &amp;c. But let us take heede how we ſweare or declare in the preſence of God, that our ſtony heart is taken from us, and that an heart of fleſh, that is, a ſoftened, mollifyed penitent heart is given us, when our hearts aſſure us, that there is no ſuch worke wrought in us, as alſo that wee intend an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of our waies, for the future, when wee intend nothing leſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quaer.</hi> What ſinnes are to be accounted the ſinnes of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? that ſo we may ſwear in judgement, knowing what we ſwear And to this purpoſe it may be queſtioned, whether the late ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious practiſes and innovations, againſt which there have beene ſo many Declamations, are to be reputed ſinnes of this Nation? and how many are or will be heartily ſorry for them, though they have beene no little cauſe of our preſent ſorrowes? as alſo whether Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall, Browniſticall, and other Separatiſticall practiſes and poſitions, connived at, if not countenanced, by thoſe who ought to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124454:16"/> ſuppreſſe and puniſh the Authors and Fautors thereof, and to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed ſinnes of the Nation; and how many will declare their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them, though our preſent ſorrowes are fomented and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by them? as further, whether plundering, robbing, and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, whether ſpeaking evill of Dignities, and ſlandering both the footſteps and perſon of the Lords Anointed; whether falſe ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and perjury, whereof our oathes of Allegiance, Supremacy, and late Proteſtation are pregnant witneſſes; are to be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſinnes of this Nation? and how many will declare their hearty ſorrow for them, though like to increaſe our ſorrowes to our being overwhelmed by them? Or whether only thoſe ſinnes not long ſince Declared by publique Order of the Lords and Commons, Feb. 15. 1642. and appointed to be read in all Churches and Chapels, &amp;c. be the ſinnes of this Nation? <hi>viz.</hi> The high contempt of Gods holy Ordinances, &amp;c. Multitudes of oathes, and blaſphemies, &amp;c. envy, contentions, and unnaturall diviſions, oppreſſion, fraud and violence, as alſo whether the blood ſhed in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and Idolatry then and ſince, are to be adjudged the ſinnes of this Nation, and our ſorrowes to be terminated in lamenting them? This I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive were fit to be declared before we ſweare or declare in the preſence of God, and as we will anſwer at the great day, &amp;c. that we are heartily ſorry for the ſinnes of this Nation. What wee doe declare our hearty ſorrow for in private, every mans owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence regulates him in: but when we make a publique, ſolemne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of our ſorrow for the whole Nations ſinnes, and enter into a ſacred covenant with God, not to commit the like ſinnes againe, it is but reaſon, that as many ſinnes of the Nation as can be thought on, at leaſt the moſt notorious, ſhould be publikely named; that ſo the people may know what ſinnes in ſpeciall they profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſorry for, and promiſe amendment of; This hath beene obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in making covenants, which were ſacred indeed, concerning Nationall ſinnes: as, in that covenant which <hi>Joſhua</hi> called upon the people to make, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. that appointed by <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 15. that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 34. and that appointed by <hi>Ezra, Ezr.</hi> 10. In all which covenants you ſhall finde the principall Nationall ſins, of which, they declared their deteſtation, and promiſed amendment, particularly Named. But indeed every one of thoſe covenants were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:124454:16"/> entred into by the command and authority of the ſupreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and it is not to be found in ſacred Writ, where ever there was any ſacred Nationall Covenant enjoyned by any, ſave by the King, or ſupreme of that Nation; or by the expreſſe authority derived from Him. But no more of this firſt part of the Covenant, it being as I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeve, the leaſt part intended by the Contrivers of it; only it is ſet in the firſt place, that looking upon that, our eyes may be ſo dazled with the glorious ſpecious religiouſneſſe of it, as not to bee able to diſcover the foule, abominable iniquity of the reſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing required in this oath, is, That we ſweare or declare in the preſence of Almighty God, that we doe abhorre and deteſt the ſaid wicked and treacherous deſigne lately diſcovered, and that we never gave, nor will give our aſſent to the execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but will according to our power and vocations oppoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the ſame, and all other of the like nature: concerning which, I make theſe foure Quaeres.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How is it poſſible for the moſt of men to ſweare this in judgement, according to the ſecond neceſſary condition of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full oath, ſeeing tis no where declared by the Lords and Commons, what that wicked and treacherous deſign was, further then in the generall (and generalls are no ſufficient ground for the abjuring any particular) only Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> hath collected ſome particulars of it in his ſpeech before mentioned: but how ſhall thouſands reach that collection? And when they have it, what proofes and teſtimonies doth he bring to convince any reaſonable man of the undoubted truth of what he ſaith? It ſeems by that very ſpeech, that himſelfe and the reſt of the Houſe of Commons, who know moſt of it, do not know it throughly, or at leaſt doubt whether they doe or not, for that pardon is offered by him in their names to any (except thoſe who are taken or fled) that ſhall within 15. dayes diſcover what he knowes of this conſpiracy. And will any man that knowes what God is, call him to witneſſe, that he abhorres and deteſts that which he doth not certainly know. Tis to be feared God will abhor that man as an extreame vaine fooliſh man, that ſhall ſo vainly and fooliſhly prophane his great name; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch a man may eaſily be induced to ſweare an abhorment and deteſtation of what God moſt likes and loves, he knowing as little of that, as of this.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:124454:17"/>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the deſigne be ſufficiently declared, though not ſo fully as ſome deſire it might be; yet Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> himſelfe hath withall declared that of it in his fore cited ſpeech, that would move any loyall Subject to make a ſecond Quaere.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether any ſuch can ſweare juſtly and righteouſly, that the deſigne diſcovered is ſuch a wicked and treacherous deſigne as ought to be abhorred &amp; deteſted by him, for beſides the intentions or aimes of it (whereof you heard in the introduction) he tells us, that for the principles of it, it did riſe from the aſhes of another de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne that failed, namely, that mutinous Petition for Peace (as he is pleaſed to honour it by his quiet Epithite) contrived in the City, and how that was to be abhorred and deteſted, let every true lover of peace judge: Then for the ſteps of it, he aſſureth us, that it came to that high ſtep at the laſt, how they might procure power and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to the action by authority from His Majeſty in the way of Commiſſion, and this, ſaith he afterwards, they did procure, and this doth not render it very horrible and deteſtable, unleſſe to thoſe that abhor to obey any Commiſſion that His Majeſty grants: So for the Actors or Agents in it, he is pleaſed to cloud ſome in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall qualifications or relations, and ſome few he cloaths with their owne names. In the generall, he tells us, that ſome Members of the City had a hand in this deſigne, whereof there were divers (they are his words) and ſome Members of both Houſes, and of the Lords Houſe (&amp; if Mr. <hi>Waller</hi> were to be credited) of the ableſt, of the beſt, and of the greateſt; in particular, he names two Gentlemen, Mr. <hi>Waller,</hi> (as though Mr. <hi>Waller</hi> an eminent Parliament man were not worthy to be reckoned amongſt the Parliament Members) and his brother in law Mr. <hi>Tomkins,</hi> (I wonder he forgot Mrs. <hi>Tomkins,</hi> who was alſo apprehended and committed; but chaſte man he mindes not women, eſpecially others mens wives) and the Lord <hi>Faulkland</hi> one of the Secretaries of State. And how the deſign ſhould deſerve to be abhorred and deteſted from ſuch mens being the prime actors in it, is beyond my skill: I ſhould rather thinke the better, then the worſe of a deſigne for ſuch actors ſake: beſides (becauſe Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> ſhould have loſt his old wont, if he had made any ſpeech (eſpecially to the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens) without throwing ſome dirt in the Kings face) we are further let know from the ſame mouth, that this matter was proſecuted in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124454:17"/> part, and agitated and promoted by thoſe which were ſent from His Majeſty, and ſeemed to be Meſſengers of Peace; and (for fear any ſhould thinke he aimed only at the Kings Meſſengers, and not at the King Himſelfe) in the ſame breath he falls foule and heavy (like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) upon the Kings gracious Meſſage of Peace, and would fain inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate that thoſe Meſſages ſent by His Majeſty were but to amuſe the people with pretences of peace, whilſt this villanous project was a working, and ſo the King is made one and (perhaps Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> will allow Him in this ſo much of His royall Title) the chiefe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and what true hearted Subject will be eaſily induced to ſay, much leſſe to ſweare that he abhorres and deteſts as wicked and treacherous that deſign, whereof his Sovereigne is not only through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed, but is (with reverence to His Sacred Majeſty be thoſe termes uſed) the chiefe Complotter and Abettor?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quar.</hi> Whether the ſwearing that I never gave my aſſent to that deſigne, be not to all thoſe that had any finger therein (and they are voiced to be many thouſands) as ſore an oath, and as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying either of their ſoules to the hazard of hell, or of their bodies and eſtates to the probability of utter ruine, as ever the oath <hi>ex officio</hi> was, ſo much cryed out upon in the world? This I am ſure of, upon the diſcovery of all the wicked, treacherous, horrid, deteſtable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes that have been in this Kingdome ſince the Reformation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther powder-treaſon, or what other ſoever, there was never the like courſe of ſoul-cruelty taken, for the inſnaring of ſo many ſoules: the Lord in His mercy looke upon them, and deliver them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether the adding of theſe words, Nor will give my aſſent to the execution thereof, but will according to my power and vocation oppoſe and reſiſt the ſame, and all other of the like nature, &amp;c. doe not argue ſtrongly that the deſigne was of that nature, that if it ſhould appeare in its owne colours, it would appeare ſo fair, that multitudes would yet aſſent to the putting it into execution? and therefore is not ſo horrid and deteſtable as ſome would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; for certainly if it were ſo, the whole Kingdome need not to be ſworne never to aſſent to the execution of it after tis once diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but to their power to oppoſe and reſiſt the ſame, and all other of the like nature; every man would of his owne accord ſet himſelfe againſt it with all his might and power.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:124454:18"/>
            <p>The third thing tendred in this oath is, That in caſe any other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne ſhall hereafter come to our knowledge, we will make ſuch timely diſcovery as we ſhall conceive may beſt conduce to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting thereof. Concerning which, I ſhall only ſtart theſe two queſtions, 1. What is to be accounted for a deſigne. 2. Whether every man that takes this oath, be not truly bound to make ſuch time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovery of whatſoever he knowes plotted, projected, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or purpoſed to the prejudice either of the King, Church or State, or any member thereof, that it may be prevented? Or whether the obligation of this oath be not reſtrained only to the diſcovery of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes againſt the two Houſes of Parliament, and eſpecially againſt thoſe Members of each Houſe againſt whom the late diſcovered de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is ſaid to be intended. And I would you durſt reſolve me free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully whether this particular oath be not ſuch a deſigne, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that knowes of the contriving thereof be not bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to diſcover what he can of it, to the preventing of the ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo many thouſand poor ſouls as are like to be hazarded therby.</p>
            <p>But to come to the main things aimed at in the impoſing this oath, thoſe indeed unto which all the preceding parts of the oath, are but a preparative, and have been themſelves prepared in a readineſſe, and reſolved upon by ſome to be gotten confirmed by an oath, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the forenamed wicked and treacherous deſigne, now made ſo advantagious to ſet of this oath withall, was ever heard of, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that many ſober judicious men doe verily ſuſpect, that rather that deſigne is declared to be ſo wicked, treacherous, horrid and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, to draw on the taking the following part of this oath, then that any part of this oath, much leſſe the whole oath it ſelfe, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon, as occaſioned by the wickedneſſe, treachery, horrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and deteſtableneſſe of that deſign, as ſome would perſwade us.</p>
            <p>We are required in the fourth place to ſweare or declare in the preſence of Almighty God, That We doe in our conſciences believe, that the forces rayſed by the two Houſes of Parliament, are rayſed and continued for their juſt defence, and for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, and Liberties of the Subject, againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rayſed by the King. Where I intreat ſatisfaction in theſe <hi>Quaeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Why is the defence of the King, heere left quite out,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:124454:18"/> when as it hath beene ſo often profeſſed and declared, by the Lords and Commons, in their ſeverall Declarations and Ordinances, that they rayſed their forces for his defence in the firſt place? It ſeemes they are afraid to ſweare that, though they have often and often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it: and why then ſhould we make their declarations ſo firme a ground of our faith, as thereupon to ſweare, that we do in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences believe, that the forces rayſed by them, were rayſed and are continued for ſuch and ſuch ends, when they themſelves will not ſweare that they were rayſed for that end, which they have ſo many times declared?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How dare any man ſweare or declare in the preſence of Almighty God, &amp;c. that he doth in his conſcience believe, that the forces rayſed by the two Houſes of Parliament, are rayſed and continued for their juſt defence, when the King hath made them ſo many gracious overtures of peace, and they have refuſed them, as appeares by ſundry Meſſages and Declarations, with the Anſwers and Replies, that have paſſed betwixt them: nay, when the King hath woed and intreated them, with ſuch ſweetnes of temper, and lownes of condeſcenſion, as never any Prince uſed towards Subjects, that they would both name the perſons, and appoint the place for a Treaty, betwixt him and them, for ſetling the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ending and quieting all differences betweene them: yet ſtill his offers have beene utterly rejected, unleſſe he would firſt take downe his Standard, and call in what Proclamations and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he had made againſt ſome of the Members of both Houſes, and their proceedings (both which his Majeſty yeelded to do, ſo that they would revoke their Declarations againſt all perſons that aſſiſted him) as alſo leave his forces, and withdraw his protection both from ſuch perſons, as were by both Houſes voted Delinquents, and from all ſuch as ſhould afterwards bee ſo voted, as you may ſee more at large in his Majeſties gracious Meſſage to both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſent from Nottingham, Auguſt 25. 1642. The Anſwer of the Lords and Commons to that Meſſage. His Majeſties reply to that anſwer. Their anſwer and their Declaration to that reply, and the former Meſſage. And can it be beleeved that the defenſive part of this war (be it juſt or unjuſt) was on their ſide, when the King was thus the offerer and ſuer for peace, and they the refuſers requiring
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124454:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:124454:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:124454:20"/> Him to yeeld to thoſe things, which could not poſſibly ſtand with His owne Honour and Safety, or with the ſafety of thoſe that are His moſt faithfull and loyall Subjects, called to His aſſiſtance by His Summons, and their Allegiance. Or can that be believed to be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive War, much leſſe a War for a juſt defence, when many of the forces raiſed by them, were raiſed, and the Kings Goods, Armes, Townes, Shipping, and whole <hi>Militia</hi> were taken from Him, and made uſe of, and held againſt him, before any the leaſt warlike of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was offered them by any Forces raiſed by the King; as hath been ſufficiently cleared, both by His Majeſties Declarations, and upon our ſad and chargeable experience. Beſides, we were told from ſeverall Pulpits, about the time of the firſt Propoſi ions for Horſe, Plate, or Money, June 10. 1642. and often times ſince, that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then in raiſing, and ſince raiſed by the Parliament, were to fetch the King from His evill Counſellours, and to remove them from Him; and this was afterwards againe promiſed to have been done within ſuch and ſuch a time, if we would contribute but the other odde forty or fifty thouſand pounds; and I aſſure you we beleeved it then, or elſe we had not parted with our monyes ſo freely. And therefore I cannot but wonder that we, who at the firſt raiſing of Forces by the Parliament, and ſome good time ſince, did verily beleeve, that thoſe forces were raiſed to catch away the King from His evill Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and to take away, or drive away His evill Counſellours from Him, promiſing our ſelves ſuch hopes of accompliſhing our deſires with ſo much eaſe and ſpeed, ſhould now ſweare that we do in our conſciences beleeve, that the ſame forces were raiſed for the juſt defence of the Parliament, as though the King had been then fetching them from their evill Counſellours, or their evill Counſellours from them. If only feares and jealouſies of the Kings intention to raiſe and leavy warre againſt His Parliament were a juſt cauſe or ground for His Parliament to leavy forces againſt Him, (which to grant would be of moſt dangerous conſequence both to King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) perhaps ſome might thinke that the preſent Parliament now aſſembled, did feare, and were jealous of ſome ſuch thing, and ſo had cauſe to provide ſuch a defence: but how can we be perſwaded in our conſciences that thoſe feares and jealouſies were juſt, when up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kings firſt knowing that ſuch feares and jealouſies did poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124454:20"/> them, He did not only declare the contrary, but did ſolemnly diſavow all ſuch intentions, profeſſing before God and the World, that he alwayes had, and then did abhorre all ſuch deſignes? And for the further clearing of His intentions in that particular, He deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all His Nobility and Councell, then attending Him, to witneſſe with Him, whether they did ſee any colour of preparations or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, that might reaſonably beget a beliefe of any ſuch deſigne, and whether they were not fully perſwaded to the contrary, &amp;c, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Nobility and Councell then preſent at yorke, being in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber above forty, made a Declaration and Profeſſion in theſe words: <hi>We whoſe names are under written, in obedience to His Majeſties deſire, and out of the duty which we owe to His Majeſties Honour, and to truth, being here upon the place, and witneſſes of His Majeſties frequent and earneſt Declarations and Profeſſions of His abhorring all deſignes of making war upon His Parliament, and not ſeeing any colour of preparations or counſels, that might reaſonably beget the beliefe of any ſuch deſigne; Do profeſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and teſtifie to all the world, that we are fully perſwaded that His Majeſty hath no ſuch intention, but that all His indeavours tend to the firm and conſtant ſetlement of the true Proteſtant Religion, the juſt priviledges of Parliament, the liberty of the Subject, the Law, Peace, and Proſperity of this Kingdome.</hi> This ſolemne Profeſſion was made by the King, and atteſted by His Nobility and Councell, June 15. 1642. which was five dayes after that the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had made certaine propoſitions and orders for the bringing in of Money, Plate, or Horſe, &amp;c. for the maintaining an Army for their defence. So that (as I ſaid before) if feares and jealouſies of the Kings intentions of raiſing and leavying War againſt His Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were a juſt cauſe or ground for his Parliament actually to raiſe or leavy forces againſt him; and if we could alſo in our conſciences believe, that ſuch feares and jealouſies did really and truly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe both Houſes; yet when it appeares by ſuch evidence (as grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better could not be given) that thoſe feares and jealouſies were not juſt: it is ſtrange to thinke what conſcience or faith, (I might adde what hope or charity) that man hath, that can anſwer or declare in the preſence of Almighty God, that he beleeveth in his conſcience that the forces raiſed by the Parliament upon that unjuſt ground or cauſe, were raiſed for their juſt defence.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:124454:21"/>3. <hi>Quar.</hi> How can any man ſweare in Judgement and in Truth, that he doth in his conſcience believe, that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament, were raiſed, and are continued for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion; when as firſt, if by the true Proteſtant Religion be meant that Proteſtant Religion, which is now eſtabliſhed (ſo far as ought can be ſaid to be eſtabliſhed) in the Church of England (as that muſt be meant, or otherwiſe we know not what the true Proteſtant Religion is, and ſo cannot take this oath in judgement) it hath been found by lamentable experience, that the true Proteſtant Religion hath been more invaded, impugned and blaſphemed by the forces raiſed by the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and their aſſiſtants and adherents, in thoſe parts where they have had the power, then ever it was ſince Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, witneſſe the many uncivill, unhumane, unchriſtian attempts, aſſaults and outrages that have been committed by Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and other Sectaries upon our eſtabliſhed Doctrine, upon our eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed worſhip and ſervice of God, upon Gods holy Ordinances, and upon thoſe ſacred places wherein all theſe were wont to meet, and preſent themſelves to us in ſuch beauty and excellencie to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable benefit and comfort. I muſt not forget, how the moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, painfull, and orthodoxall Proteſtant Divines (they that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, when the Proteſtant Religion ſuffered moſt by another faction, bare the heat and burden of the oppoſition, and ſtood in the gap againſt Arminianiſme, and other innovations) have been ſince the raiſing of forces by the Parliament, and by the power thereof, abuſed, impriſoned, and cruelly handled, when others that then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted their ſtations, have been magnified and extolled, nay, when drunken, debauched, innovating drones, that have contributed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintenance of the Parliaments forces, have been conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at and favoured, and if by chance apprehended, ſpeedily diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſet at liberty. He muſt have a ſtrong faith, and a ſtretching conſcience, that can beleeve in his conſcience, that theſe are markes or ſignes of defending the true Proteſtant Religion. If this be their defending of it, God ſend us our old Defendor thereof once againe reſtabliſhed in His Throne, and let theſe new defenders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves. Secondly, the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament did, no longer ſince then in March laſt, declare, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124454:21"/> publiſh to the world in that Ordinance of theirs, for the ſpeedy rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and leavying of money for the maintainance of the Army raiſed by the Parliament, that the only Cauſes for which they had raiſed, and did then continue an Army and Forces, were, firſt, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary defence of themſelves (which may be ſomewhat more eaſily believed then for their juſt defence.) Seconly, for the neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this Kingdome from forraigne invaſions, a defence not now mentioned. And thirdly, for the bringing of notorious offenders to condigne puniſhment, a thing alſo (as was before hinted) altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgotten in this new oath. And if the Lords and Commons themſelves have ſo lately declared and acknowleded, that theſe were the only cauſes, for which they raiſed, and then continued their army and forces, they have no cauſe to take offence at any that ſhall not believe, that the ſame forces were raiſed and continued, for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion. I praiſe God I have no ſuch Moon-faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Quar.</hi> How can any man ſweare in truth, That he doth in his conſcience believe, that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and continued for the defence of the liberties of the Subject, when by the raiſing and continuing of theſe Forces, firſt, the liberty of enjoying their owne goods, chattells, or lands. Secondly, the liberty of their trading and traffiquing. Thirdly, the liberty of their perſons. Fourthly, the liberty their conſciences towards God, their King, and their fellow-brethren. Fifthly, the liberty of their very lives, is dayly and hourely either taken or endeavoured to be taken from the beſt of Subjects, and all theſe contrary to the liberty of the eſtabliſhed knowne Lawes of this Land. Indeed, to Bankrupts and Spendthrifts, to Rogues, Theeves, Murtherers, and ſuch like, there is ſuch politick liberty of ſpoyling, robbing, plundering, and killing yeelded, to Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and other Sectaries, ſuch Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall liberty of Conventicle, prating and printing permitted, and to all ſorts of factious, ſeditious, rebellious Miſcreants, ſuch liberty of lying, rayling, and blaſpheming indulged, as the like was never heard of, much leſſe tollerated and countenanced in any Chriſtian Common-wealth. And though we had ſuch faith as that we could beleeve that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament were raiſed for the defence of the liberties of the Subject, yet when we poore oppreſſed, ſpoyled, and almoſt ruined Subjects, ſee, feele, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124454:22"/> complaine, that the fruits and effects thereof are ſo deſtructively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereunto; we cannot poſſibly believe, that they are ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the defence of our liberties; and therefore it is but juſt to deſire, that they, and only they be required to ſweat they do believe this, who have hitherto enjoyed their liberties.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Quar.</hi> How can any man ſweare in Judgement and Truth, that he doth in his conſcience beleeve, that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes, &amp;c. were raiſed, and are continued for the juſt defence of theſe three things named in this oath, when that which ſhould juſtifie the defence of them, or any of them (if ought could poſſibly juſtifie it in thoſe wayes practiſed by them) I meane the knowne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Law of this Land, is not only violated and juſtled out of place and power, but alſo quite left out of all defence and protection; now they come to ſweare or declare before the Lord, that thoſe things are, which they intend to defend. What may bee the reaſon thinke you, why in former Declarations and Ordinances of the Lords and Commons, it hath beene often profeſſed, that one maine end of their raiſing forces was for the defence of the Lawes of this Land, and yet now in this new oath, when they reckon up the main ends of rayſing and continuing the very ſame forces, the Laws of the Land are not once named. Certainly we might as ſafely ſweare, that we doe in our conſciences believe, that the ſayd forces were rayſed, and are continued for the defence of the Lawes of the Land, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the whole Land knowes that by thoſe forces, the Lawes of the Land have beene and are quite ſilenced and null'd) as we can ſweare that we doe in our conſciences believe, that they were rayſed and are continued for the juſt defence of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and are for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, and liberties of the Subject. Only the Lawes of the Land are likely to bring in ſuch an heavy accuſation and ſore judgement againſt thoſe that have taken up Armes in this cauſe on the Parliament ſide, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the ſpecious pretences of fair ſeeming ends, and are ſo Diametrically, or point blank to all Arbitrary power, that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving that thoſe forces raiſed by the Parliament, were raiſed, and are continued for the defence of thoſe Lawes might well be ſpared.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Quar.</hi> How can any man ſweare either in Judgement or in Righteouſneſſe or in Truth, That he doth in his conſcience beleeve
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124454:22"/> that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes, &amp;c. were raiſed, and are continued for their owne juſt defence, and for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, and liberties of the Subject, againſt the forces raiſed by the King; when the King hath not only often and often profeſſed and declared, but at ſundry times moſt ſolemnly and deeply vowed, proteſted and ſworne (his Nobility and Councell, in number above forty, and in eſtate, honour, and worth not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralled throughout the Kingdome, atteſting and profeſſing the ſame, as you heard before) that he ever intended the ſafety and preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all three, and when he did raiſe any forces, that he raiſed them to make good thoſe intentions, and (&amp; to Gods glory, His Majeſties honour, and his Subjects comfort and benefit, be it publiſhed) hath to his utmoſt made them all good, in all places where his forces have been quartered ſince the firſt raiſing them to this preſent, as both his Armies, and many thouſands more are ready to depoſe it if that would ſatisfie. For my part, I aſcribe ſo much to the word of a King, and in particular to the word of pious, Religious King <hi>Charles,</hi> that what he declares in point of Truth, eſpecially concerning his Royall Intentions, I think my ſelfe bound in conſcience to beleeve, before all the Declarations of all others in the world; how much more, when ſo pious and religious a King as he is, hath ſo often vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſworne ſuch and ſuch things, ought all His Subjects (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally having all ſworne to maintaine His Honour againſt all that ſhall doe ought to the prejudice thereof,) ſo to honour Him, as to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and beleeve his Vow and Oath, before the Declaration of a few of His Subjects, who have ſtrained (to ſay the leaſt, and with the moſt modeſty and reverence) their former oaths made to their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigne, both by raiſing forces againſt Him, and by entring into this preſent vow and covenant againſt Him, and the forces raiſed by Him, as will be further demonſtrated by and by. It is well knowne to all knowing and underſtanding men, that a King is not capable of having thoſe by aimes and ends in making or taking an Oath, or of thoſe many temptations of breaking or violating an oath when it is made or taken, that ſome of His Subjects may have. And though it ſhould be granted by all (as we know it is not) that the Lords and Commons remaining in the two Houſes of Parliament, are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Body of the Kingdome, to doe for them, as well as to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124454:23"/> conſult; yet certainly no ſober man will grant that every body in the Kingdome is bound to act and doe whatſoever they injoyne, be it good or evill, much leſſe that they ought to ſwear, that they doe in their conſciences beleeve whatſoever they do declare or ſwear: and although it were acknowledged that they are the repreſentative Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Kingdome, and ſo repreſentative, that the whole Kingdom were bound, either to doe, or ſuffer for not doing, whatſoever they enjoyne (as tis knowne we are not unleſſe our Head did conſent, and joyne with them) yet, ſtill I hope, none thinke them the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Soule of the Kingdome, ſo that, whatſoever they believe, or ſweare they believe, our ſouls are bound to beleeve the ſame. Nay further, had the Lords and Commons ſworne expreſly and punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes, &amp;c. were raiſed and continued for thoſe three forementioned ends, yet ſtill for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before alledged, I cannot ſee why we ſhould ſwear that we doe believe the ſame: But when the Lords and Commons themſelves, that were the raiſers of thoſe forces, ſwear only, that they do in their conſciences believe that thoſe forces were raiſed, and are continued for thoſe ends (as being it ſeems fully perſwaded ſo, either by the cloſe Committee, or by ſome others that knew the certainty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.) One would thinke it were an act of charity and faith ſufficient, for others to be their compurgators ſo far, as to ſwear, that they doe believe that thoſe Lords and Commons doe believe ſo; and that it is too great a preſumption, to ſwear that they do in their conſciences believe that it was, and is ſo indeed. Believe me in any other caſe, if any other perſons, whoſe truth and integrity is beſt knowne to us, had acknowledged that they themſelves had done this or that, and being ſuſpected, that they had done it for ſome evill intent or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſhould ſwear only that they doe in their conſciences believe, that they did it for ſuch, or ſuch an end, moſt fair and juſt, their very ſwearing ſo would cauſe more ſuſpition of them, then if they had held their peace, and ſaid nothing.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How dare any man ſweare or declare in the preſence of Almighty God, &amp;c. that he doth in his conſcience believe, that the forces raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament, are raiſed and continued for their juſt defence, and for the defence of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and liberties of the Subject, againſt the forces rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124454:23"/> by the King; when ſo to ſweare or declare, is to ſweare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in Gods preſence that he doth in his conſcience believe, that the forces raiſed by the King are raiſed and continued for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and ruine, at leaſt for the extream damage and detriment of all the ſame things? And what a hard caſe is it, that a man muſt be put to ſuch an oath, as to ſweare not only that he doth believe well of both Houſes of Parliamen, but alſo that he doth believe ſo much evill of a good King? as were He the worſt of Kings, worſe could not be thought of Him, all things conſidered? Why perhaps there may be ſome of ſo loyall and juſt thoughts towards their Sovereigne, and yet withall of ſo charitable and reverentiall thoughts towards both Houſes of Parliament, as to thinke that the forces on each part were raiſed and continued for the ſame ends, and they (thoſe three mentioned) only moſt unhappily differd in the meanes and wayes of accompliſhing thoſe ends. And what ſhall theſe poore ſouls do, when they cannot ſatisfie the Parliament by taking this oath, but they muſt thereby abandon all loyall thoughts of their King? Lord be thou their Directour.</p>
            <p>It followeth in the oath, as an inference inforced from the laſt thing believed and ſworne, <hi>I do here in the preſence of Almighty God declare, vow, and covenant, that I will according to my power and vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſſiſt the forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes of Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the forces raiſed by the King, without their conſent.</hi> Concerning which part of the oath, that I may ſtill keep withing the preſcribed bounds of a lawfull oath, I deſire theſe <hi>Quaeries</hi> may be cleared.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quaer.</hi> What is here meant by Vocation, that ſo we may ſwear in judgement knowing what we ſwear? whether are we to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by Vocation, that ordinary courſe of life, or externall profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereunto God doth ordinarily call men, and where he doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally place them? as when ſome are called to be Paſtors and Teachers in the Church, others to be fed and taught; ſome are called to be Maſters, others to be Servants; ſome are called to be Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, others are called to be Tradeſmen, &amp;c. or whether by Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here, may not be underſtood ſome extraordinary calling by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inſpiration, divine revelation or the like; as certainly ſome ſuch calling muſt be preſuppoſed, or elſe I cannot ſee what warrant they can pretend for the aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting any forces againſt their Sovereigne.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124454:24"/> This <hi>Quare</hi> I could not baulke, becauſe the uſing of this expreſſion, <hi>According to my Vocation,</hi> is not any where to be found, that I know of any oath that hath been taken in this Nation, though the other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, <hi>According to my power,</hi> hath been uſuall in moſt or all our promiſſorie oaths; which makes me to think that ſome Divine or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the framer and contriver of this new oath, or at leaſt had a great hand in it (howſoever it was pretended to have been ſuddenly framed by ſome Members of the Houſe of Commons upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the great deſigne) and being called to that calling, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience minded him ſomewhat of the unlawfulneſſe and unſeemli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a Miniſter of the Goſpel of peace to be an aſſiſtant in war, eſpecially in ſuch a war; or elſe rather he thought, that the adding of this limitation, <hi>According to my vocation,</hi> would excuſe him both from contributing much money to the warre, as alſo from hazarding his owne perſon in it (as ſome of their furious brethren to their ſhame and confuſion have done) ſo that he did but in his preaching, and by his praying, thoſe two glorious, but now prophaned and blaſphemed Ordinances, intice and ſtir up others thereunto: But then I cannot but ſtill wonder why the Lords ſhould each of them ſweare, <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my vocation, &amp;c.</hi> I believe if one ſhould aske any of their Lordſhips what vocation he is of, he would not take it well; though for the Houſe of Commons, we know divers of them are of ſeverall vocations, and ſo this limitation might become them well enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How any man that profeſſeth himſelf to be either of the ſame judgement with the Church of England, and with the glorious Martyrs, and renowned Divines, and other learned Worthies, that have ſince the Reformation lived in this Church, or of the ſame judgement with any other of the reformed Churches, and the moſt renowned Members thereof, can ſwear in Judgement, that he will aſſiſt any forces raiſed by Subjects, againſt the forces raiſed by their Sovereign, when it hath been ſo fully and amply declared by all thoſe Churches, and by their chiefe Worthies ſucceſſively in all times, that tis altogether unlawfull for any Subjects to take up Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Sovereigne, though a Tyrant, though a perſecuter of the Goſpel, though never ſo wicked and ungodly, as is to be ſeen in our owne Homilies againſt Rebellion, in the Acts and Monuments of our Martyrs, in the Harmony of Confeſſions of the reformed Churches,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124454:24"/> in <hi>Luther, Calvin, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lampadius, Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inglius, Buder, Peter Martyr, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Bullinger,</hi> and many other forraigne Divines, as alſo in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of our moſt famous and pious. Engliſh Divines, whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, with the teſtimonies of many others, I am credibly informed had been long ſince, for the ſatisfaction of thoſe that queſtion it, faithfully publiſhed by an orthodox Divine (now a priſoner in Ely Houſe) had not ſome of the Houſe of Commons prevented him by ſeizing upon his book w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilſt it was in the Preſſe, as fearing all ſuch information of the people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How any man that hath taken either the oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, or the oath of Allegiance, or the late Proteſtation, can without perjury <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſweare, that he will according to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer aſſiſt the forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the forces raiſed by the King, ſeeing all thoſe three oaths are ſo flatly and fully contrary to this part of this oath, of all the reſt; as firſt in the oath of Supremacy we ſweare, <hi>That we did te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, and declare in our conſciences, that the Kings Highneſſe is the only ſupreme Governour of this Realm, &amp;c. and as well in all ſpirituall or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall things or cauſes, as temporall;</hi> and if ſo, the juſt power of raiſing forces, and other power of the ſword doth only belong to Him, and none ought to raiſe any forces, or exerciſe any other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the ſword, without His conſent, and without expreſſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived from Him; the power of the ſword being that which principally makes and maintaines the Supremacy, and therefore aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed by the Apoſtle to the ſupreme power only, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>He bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the ſword in vaine, for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wrath upon him that doth evill:</hi> and to grant the Parliament a juſt power of raiſing forces without the Kings conſent (much more to grant them power of raiſing Arms contrary to His Proclamation, and other expreſſe Commands, and they againſt the forces raiſed by the King) is to ſet up two ſupreme Powers in one Kingdome, and ſo two ſwords one againſt another, and both to the ruine of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Againe, we ſweare in the ſame oath, That <hi>we would bear faith and true Allegiance to the Kings Highneſſe his Heires, &amp;c. and that we would to our power aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences, and Authorities granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, his heirs, &amp;c.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124454:25"/> or united and annexed to the Imperial Crowne of the Realm.</hi> As alſo in the oath of Allegeance we ſwear, That <hi>we would beare faith and Allegeance to His Majeſty, His Heires, &amp;c. and that we would defend Him and them to the utmoſt of our power againſt all conſpiracies and attempte whatſoever, which ſhould be made againſt his or their perſons, their Crowne and dignity, either by reaſon of any Sentence or Declaration of the Pope or otherwiſe; and that we would doe our beſt endeavour to diſcloſe and make knowne unto his Majeſty, his Heires, &amp;c. all treaſons, and traiterous conſpiracies, which we ſhould know or heare of, to be againſt him or any of them.</hi> And laſtly, in our late Proteſtation, we ſweare to maintaine and defend with our lives and powers and eſtates according to the duty of our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, His Majeſties royall Perſon, Honour, and Eſtate; and to our power, and as far as lawfully we may, to oppoſe, and by all good meanes to endeavour to bring to condigne puniſhment all ſuch as ſhould either by force, plots, conſpiracies, or otherwiſe do any thing to the contrary. Now whether the aſſiſting of forces raiſed by ſome of the Kings Subjects againſt the forces raiſed by the King, be not expreſly and fully contrary to all theſe particulars promiſed and ſworn in all theſe oaths, let any indifferent man judge; as (to name ſome contrarieties for many) 1. Whether it be not uſurpation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment upon the Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences or Authority granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, and united and annexed to the Imperiall Crowne, and ſo flatly contrary to the oath of Supremacy. 2. Whether it be not an attempt, if not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, made againſt either the Kings Perſon, or his Crowne and Dignity, and ſo fully contrary to the oath of Allegeance. 3. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not hazardous to the Kings perſon, ſcandalous to His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and detrimentall to His Eſtate, and ſo directly contrary to the late Proteſtation. Laſtly, whether it be not a breach of that faith, duty, and loyall ſubjection, which both by the bond of Allegeance, and by the commandement of Almighty God (as the Statute ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth 7. <hi>Jac.</hi> cap. 6) we ought to beare to His Majeſty, and ſo contrary to all three oaths, and to his expreſſe command, who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to witneſſe both in them and this. For my part, I appeale only to that which is moſt concerned, and in moſt perill, I meane the conſcience of every one that hath taken the former oaths, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to this, wiſhing that every one that hath forgotten whether
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124454:25"/> he ever tooke the oaths of Supremacy and Allegeance or not (as I feare there are not a few ſuch) that he would conſult with himſelfe, and the Statutes which enjoyne thoſe oaths, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Elizab c.</hi> 1. and 3. <hi>Jacob. c.</hi> 4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. <hi>Jacob. c.</hi> 6. the comparing of this new oath with thoſe former oaths would occaſion a multitude of <hi>Quaeres</hi> had ſome men the liberty of ſtarting them; I ſhall be bold on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to point at one which in order to the preceding <hi>Quaeres</hi> upon this part of this oath makes the fourth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Whether the taking of a new oath, and recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and tendring it to others, which is contrary to the oath of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, as this new oath is, do not render the perſons ſo doing, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the breach, and liable to the penalty of that branch in that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute 3. <hi>Jacob. cap.</hi> 4. expreſſed in theſe words: And further bee it ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon or perſons at any time, after the tenth of June, ſhall either upon the ſeas, or in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, within the Dominions of the Kings Majeſty, his heires, or ſucceſſors, put in practiſe to abſolve, perſwade, or withdraw any of the Subjects of the Kings Majeſty, or of his heires, or ſucceſſors of this Realme of England, from their naturall obedience to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, his heires, or ſucceſſors, or to reconcile them to the Pope or See of Rome, or to move them or any of them, to promiſe obedience to any pretended authority of the See of Rome, or to any other Prince, State, or Potentate, That then every ſuch perſon, their procurers, counſellors, ayders and maintainers, knowing the ſame, ſhall bee to all intents adjudged Traitors, and being thereof lawfully convicted, ſhall have judgement, ſuffer and forfeyt, as in caſes of high Treaſon.</p>
            <p>And if any ſuch perſon, as aforeſaid, &amp;c. ſhall be willingly abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or withdrawne as aforeſaid, or willingly reconciled, or promiſe obedience to any ſuch pretended authority, Prince, State, or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, as aforeſaid, That every ſuch perſon or perſons, their procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, counſellors, ayders, and maintainers, knowing the ſame, ſhall be to all intents adjudged Traytors, and being thereof lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, ſhall have judgement, ſuffer, and forfeyt, as in caſe of high treaſon. See the like ſtat. 23. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh, that you would propound this Quaere privately to ſome honeſt, able, faithfull Lawyer, and let me know his reſolution, it being of great and high concernment.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:124454:26"/>5. <hi>Quar.</hi> Whether the ſwearing, that we will according to our power and vocation, aſſiſt the forces rayſed and continued by both Houſes of Parliament, againſt the forces rayſed by the King, doth not ſwear us up to do that, which will bring us within compaſſe of high Treaſon, declared by that ſtatute of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. wherein it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the King at the requeſt of the Lords and Commons in that Parliament aſſembled, That it is high Treaſon to compaſſe or imagine the death of our Lord the King, or of our Lady his Queene, or of their eldeſt ſonne and heire: or if a man doe levy warre againſt our Lord the King in his Realme, or be adherent to the Kings enemies in his Realme, giving to them ayd and comfort in the Realme or elſwhere, and thereof be probably attainted of open deed by people of their condition, I believe, when the eſtabliſhed Law of this Land comes to be in force againe, it will puzzle all the Lawyers of this Kingdome to aſſoile us of that guilt, by the ſubtilleſt interpretations they can invent? And truly I doe not yet value eyther ſoule or body at ſo low a rate, as to venture eyther upon ſuch an hazard.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that it ſhould not be found high treaſon, yet I have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Quaere to put concerning this oath, that will make many looke, before they leap into it, leſt they thereby leap out of a great part of their eſtates, and that is this.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Quar.</hi> Whether the taking this part of this oath and practiſing accordingly, do not expoſe as many as have Offices, Fees, Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Honours, Lordſhips, Caſtles, Mannors, Lands, Tenements, and other poſſeſſions and hereditaments of the Kings gifts and grants, (which are throughout this Kingdome a conſiderable number) to an inavoydable forfeiture thereof, whenas by thoſe two ſtatutes, <hi>viz.</hi> 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. it is enacted, That every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons within the Realme of England or Wales, that have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch offices, fees, annuities, &amp;c. and doth not in perſon attend upon the King being in perſon in warres againſt his enemies, and rebells within the ſame Realme or without, for repreſſing and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of them and their miſchievovs purpoſe, ſhall forfeit all his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, fees, annuities, &amp;c, and that all the Kings gifts, grants, and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents, wherby they enjoy them, ſhall be utterly annulled, void, of none effect, and at the Kings pleaſure: unleſſe it be ſuch, as have ſpeciall licence under the Kings ſigne manuall or ſignet, or elſe have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:124454:26"/> ſuch unſeigned ſickeneſſe, letting, or diſeaſe, that he may not in his perſon come to doe that attendance.</p>
            <p>The ſame Statutes, as they require ſuch attendance upon the Kings perſon in his warres more eſpecially, from ſuch men as have any promotion from the King, ſo they declare alſo, that every Subject by the duty of his Allegiance is bounden to ſerve and aſſiſt his Prince and ſovereigne Lord at all ſeaſons when need ſhall require, and what he ſhall be adjudged worthy to forfeit or ſuffer, that ſhall fail of that duty, any knowing Lawyer will ſoon informe you.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Quaer.</hi> How can any man ſweare in Righteouſneſſe, that he will aſſiſt the forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the forces raiſed by the King; when by the Lawes of the Land it is enacted, that no manner of perſon or perſons, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he or they be that attend upon the King and ſovereigne Lord of this Land for the time being in his perſon, &amp;c. or be in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by his commandment in his warres within this Land or without, ſhall for the ſame be either convict or attaint of high Treaſon, or any other offences, either by act of Parliament or otherwiſe by any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Law, whereby to ſuffer any loſſe or damage, but for that deed and ſervice to be utterly diſcharged for any vexation, trouble or loſſe, and if any act or acts, or other proceſſe after the time of that act ſhall happen to be made contrary to that act, that then that act or acts, or other proceſſe of the Law whatſoever ſhall ſtand and be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly void, 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder then, if in this new covenant, when we ſwear to aſſiſt the forces raiſed and continued by the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the forces raiſed by the King, that neceſſary reſtriction or limitation (ſo carefully inſerted in the late Proteſtation,) <hi>viz.</hi> As far as lawfully I may, be here in this oath wholy omitted; when as the eſtabliſhed Laws of the Land are in ſo many things ſo fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all ſuch aſſiſtance, that if we had ſworne only to aſſiſt the Parliaments forces againſt the Kings forces, as farre as lawfully we may, we had ſworne not to aſſiſt them at all, but to our utmoſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and repreſſe them.</p>
            <p>And whereas tis further intimated in this part of this oath, and in that which followeth, by way of aggravation againſt the Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they were raiſed without the conſent of both Houſes of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:124454:27"/> Parliament: I would willingly bend an eare either to <hi>Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> himſelfe (that great pretender to Law and Parliaments, though a Traitor to both as well as to his King) or to any other that ſhall pleaſe to tell me of any one act of Parliament, of any other eſtabliſhed Law of this Land, that doth allow the two Houſes of Parliament in any caſe whatſoever to raiſe any forces without the conſent of the King, much leſſe againſt the Kings conſent, and againſt the Kings forces; or (which is a bold chalenge of one that is no Lawyer) that doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly binde the King in no caſe whatſoever (no not for His owne ſafety and preſervation, nor for the ſafety and preſervation of His Kingdome, of the true Religion, of the Lawes of the Land, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject, &amp;c.) to raiſe any forces without the conſent of the two Houſes of Parliament. And if in any caſe the King may raiſe forces without the conſent of the two Houſes of Parliament, then ſurely much more in the preſent caſe, when not only all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of conſent from the two Houſes was impoſſibilitated, but the two Houſes themſelves had actually raiſed forces without the Kings conſent, and had ſeiſed upon the Kings Caſtles and Armes, and held them againſt Him. But I have ſtayed too long amongſt Acts and Statutes, the proper Authenticks of Lawyers: I returne to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, of whom I deſire to favour moſt; and with his leave and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I paſſe to the next clauſe of the oath; and that is yet more deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, if more deſperate can be, for having ſworne only in this laſt clauſe, That we will according to our power, &amp;c. aſſiſt the publick open forces raiſed and continued by the two Houſes of Parliament againſt the forces raiſed by the King, we are required in the next clauſe to ſweare; That we will according to our power alſo aſſiſt all private and cloſe conſpirators in whatſoever they ſhall attempt or doe, either againſt the Kings forces, or againſt the King Himſelfe, His Queen, the Prince, or any other, ſo that what they attempt or doe, be but for the advantage of both Houſes, and their forces now on foot; the words import no leſſe, he that runs may read it.</p>
            <p>And will likewiſe aſſiſt all other perſons that ſhall take this oath in what they ſhall doe in purſuance thereof, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a hard ſaying, who can beare it? nay that is too too gentle a ſaying for it? This is a moſt terrible ſaying, what Chriſtian but will tremble at it?</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:124454:27"/>
            <p>For firſt, What if the Turke, Pope, or Spaniard ſhall by their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents or inſtruments, do ought in the purſuance of this buſineſſe (as I verily beleeve ſome of them have done too much) if thoſe agents or inſtruments will but take this oath (as certainly they may with no ſmall advantage to their Maſters) muſt I vow and covenant to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What if any Jeſuits, or Jeſuited Papiſts ſhall joyne in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Cauſe? Muſt I ſweare to aſſiſt them? Why then is there in the Introduction to this oath ſuch a loud complaint made of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Army now on foot &amp;c. It ſeems, that it is not their being Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh that troubles them, but their being an Army againſt their deſign, for it appears by this clauſe of this oath, That if an army of Papiſts would aſſiſt them againſt the Kings Forces, and take but this oath, they ſhould have their oaths, and the oaths of as many as they can prevaile with to ſwear that they will aſſiſt them in whatſoever they ſhall doe in that way. I will not queſtion their aſſiſting of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Browniſts, and other Sectaries, they are ſo deep in their prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and aſſiſtance already, that there needs no ſwearing to aſſiſt them.</p>
            <p>But what thinke you in the third place, what if Monopolizers, Patentees, Projectors, ſcandalous Miniſters, &amp;c. which not long ſince were rendred the very bane of the Kingdome, and unworthy to live, nay what if notorious Rogues, Theeves, Plunderers, Robbers, Murderers, inceſtuous perſons, perjured perſons, Traitors and Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinates ſhall to former impieties adde the taking of this oath? am I not likewiſe required by this clauſe to ſwear to aſſiſt them, and every of them? to leave perſons, and come to things; perhaps the things wherein I muſt ſweare to aſſiſt all perſons that ſhall take this oath, will prove ſuch, as that I may lawfully ſweare to aſſiſt any perſons in, be they otherwiſe never ſo lewd and wicked. Well, ſuppoſe that, (though as God abhorres wicked mens ſacrifices, ſo where I know them to be ſuch, I like not to be their aſſiſtants or companions in their moſt ſpecious undertakings) yet let us examine what things they are that we muſt ſweare to aſſiſt them in; why the oath it ſelfe tells us plainly, and without any limitation, that we muſt aſſiſt them in what they ſhall doe in the purſuance thereof, that is (as far as I am able to conſtrue it) in whatſoever they ſhall doe for the aſſiſtance or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:124454:28"/> advantage of the forces raiſed by the two Horſes, againſt the forces raiſed by the King: and here ariſeth a fourth Quaere, (quiet it that can) What if any perſon or perſons ſhall in the purſuance of this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, rob, ſpoyle, or plunder any of the Kings Subjects? What if he, or they ſhall betray, abuſe, or murder their owne fathers, brothers, maſters or friends? What if they ſhall preach or print horrid lies and bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hemies, beſides old rotten ends of long ſince condemned Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies mixt with new Sedition, Treaſon, and Rebellion? Nay what if any perſon of perſons ſhall in that purſuance mentioned, attempt the depoſing of our Sovereigne Lord the King, or (which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more to be trembled at in the very naming) the killing of Him. His royall Conſort, and all His hopefull Children? Doe not as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as take this oath, ſweare to aſſiſt them, and every of them that ſhall commit theſe and all theſe deteſtable execrable wickedneſſes, when they ſwear that they will aſſiſt every one that ſhall take this oath, without exception, in whatſoever he ſhall doe in the purſuance of that their Cauſe, without reſtriction? Yes doubtleſſe, unleſſe they ſweare with ſome mentall reſervation, which is Jeſuiticall, or with ſome reſervation orall (as tis ſaid ſome of the Lords tooke the whole oath) which in effect made it no oath, but a mock-oath. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that forenamed limitation, As far as lawfully I may, might well have been here alſo inſerted, had it ſeemed good to the Contrivers of this oath. But tis likely they have ſome cauſe to the contrary; or whether they did or not, I am ſure we have juſt cauſe from hence to ſuſpect, that this oath aimes at more then yet the Contrivers of it dare diſcover. And let them now aſcend never ſo high, or dig never ſo deep, be it to dare Heaven with an attempt, or to ranſacke Hell for one, this clauſe of this oath once taken, will aſſure them of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>There is but one piece more of this new oath, beſides the cloſe and ſeale of all, that remaines to be opened, viz. <hi>And will directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly adhere unto, nor ſhall willingly aſſiſt the forces raiſed by the King, without the conſent of both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> and that hath beene already examined in the unveyling the preceding parts thereof. All therefore that I ſhall ſuperadde concerning it ſhall be wrapt up in this one Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Queſt. What if God in his infinite mercy to this Nation, ſhall
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124454:28"/> pleaſe ſo to open the eyes of the blinded miſled people thereof, or ſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lop their dull and heavy ears, and ſo to moliſie and humble their hard rebellious hearts, that yet once againe they ſhall ſee with their eyes, heare with their eares, and underſtand with their hearts thoſe things that belong to their peace and happineſſe? and to that purpoſe, both ſee and hear and underſtand, that their Sovereign Lord the King is in the right, and the Lords and Commons in Parliament are in an error? that tis he that hath raiſed forces (or rather God moſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly by Him) for the ſafety of His owne Perſon, and for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the true Proteſtant Religion, the Laws of the Land, the juſt priviledges of Parliament, and the liberties of the Subject, when others raiſed tumults, commotions and rebellion, to the inexpreſſible perill of the utter ruining and ſubverting of all thoſe our Nations greateſt bleſſings? what I ſay, if God of his unſpeakable mercy to this Nation, and juſt vindication of Truth, ſhall make us to ſee and acknowledge this? Shall we before hand ſo ſwear our ſelves out of all mercy, by this laſt clauſe of this oath, that either we will not dare to acknowledge it when God ſhall manifeſt it; or if we do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, we cannot either directly or indirectly make peace with, or ſubminiſter helpe and aſſiſtance unto thoſe forces of our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, raiſed up by God for his owne Glory, our Sovereignes ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and our own, and our poſterities preſervation and comfort, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perjured? Lord keep thou our feet out of this ſnare.</p>
            <p>Thus have I at laſt gotten through each part of this Covenant, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only that which I but now called the ſeale thereof, in theſe words: <hi>And this vow and covenant I make in the preſence of God the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intention to performe the ſame, as I ſhall anſwer it at the great day when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed.</hi> Had this vow and covenant been made only of ſuch things as are true and juſt, and known ſo to be unto all that are required to enter into it, the ſetting of this Seal had been requiſite and neceſſary; but the Vow and Covenant it ſelfe being ſuch (as it appears to be by the ſearching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it) that no one intire clauſe of it can be taken (at leaſt not of the promiſſory part, without tranſgreſſing fouly againſt one or more of thoſe three inſeparable conditions of a juſtifiable oath; in my apprehenſion, the requiring us to ſet to this Seale ſhould be enough to terrifie all men (that know what the affixing to ſuch a ſeal mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124454:29"/> from daring to enter into the place where this Covenant is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, much more from entring into this Covenant it ſelfe, and ſetting this ſoul-ſcarring Seale thereunto. For how ſhall I (may every ſuch man ſay) how ſhall I make ſuch a Covenant as this in the preſence of Almighty God the ſearcher of all hearts? when he that ſearcheth my heart knoweth that ſome parts of it I underſtand not what they mean, ſome parts I doubt of whether they be true, ſome parts I know to be illegall and unjuſt; and to ſome parts I have already once, twice or oftner ſworne the juſt contrary, calling the ſame Almighty God the ſearcher of all hearts to witneſſe thereunto, and to be avenged on me if I made it not good? And how ſhall I pawne all the mercy which I hope for at that great and terrible day of the Lord to all the wrath and judgement that ſhall be revealed upon the truth of my intention of performing this Covenant? when either my heart alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tells me, or may ſoone tell me, that I intend no ſuch thing, or to be ſure it will be told me in that day when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed that no ſuch thing ought to have been ſo much as intended, much leſſe ſworne by me?</p>
            <p>Thus have you (moſt intimate of friends) both my judgement of this new Oath, and my earneſt requeſt for yours, ſeconded with your prayers. If you ſhould chance to have raſhly taken this oath your ſelfe, ere theſe <hi>Quares</hi> come to your hands, (as who in theſe tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, turning times, can be confident of any mans conſtancy?) yet I hope, through Gods bleſſing upon them, they may ſo work upon you, as to cauſe you to reflect upon what you have done with ſorrow, and to reſolve againſt the doing what you have thereby inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately promiſed, with ſpirit and courage; knowing that it is a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved caſe in point of conſcience, That in raſh and unlawfull Oathes, <hi>Qui non mutat, dupliciter peccat, &amp; quia injuſte juravit, &amp; quia facit quid non debet:</hi> He that alters not his reſolution, doubleth his ſinne, becauſe he both ſweareth unjuſtly, and then doeth that which hee ought not to do. And holy David did exceedingly bleſſe both God, the advice of a woman, and the woman her ſelfe that gave it, for keeping him off from performing a raſh and unjuſt Vow that he had made, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. You have ſeene my fidelity, let me ſee yours; and whatſoever anſwer you returne, direct it to my Brother of Chriſt Church, who is as I my ſelfe am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull friend and Brother in the Lord Chriſt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:124454:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
